
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Christo[phylo] Stiltzio.

Gratia et pax a domino per Christum.

Sic foenerata est apud nos epistola tua, Christophile nobis dilecte [!], ut epistolii loco libellum remittamus, ne omnino ignaviae silentiique nos adcusare possis. Verum scio, quod iam dudum torvo aspectu nostra intuearis, Ioannis instigationem et meam imprimis temeritatem culpes. Sed mitius quęso, mavult enim per me Ioannes respondere, quam solus tantam sarcinam subire. Pro me nihil aliud dico, quam quod salutem illam tuam mihi impręcatam remunerare eo animo voluerim, ut videres eam mihi fuisse suavissimam. Accipe ergo, Christophyle nobis dilecte, quod communi utriusque nomine respondemus.

Et principio neminem plane contemnimus, quando communi domino quivis aut stet aut cadat et nemo ad hanc doctrinam dei veniat, nisi pater traxerit eum, adeo non egemus alieno subsidio, quod pultem a deo potius quam hominibus intritam exedere tentet. De nobis nihil ardui pollicemur, interim certo certiores sumus doctrinam e lege, prophetis et apostolis depromptam et nostro tempore praedicatam adeo non posse falsam esse, ut falsum non est coelos nunquam ruituros. Ideo nihil amplius nobis tribuimus quam fideles reliqui, quam tuus etiam, imo et noster Ambrosius, cum diceret: «Nolo nobis credatur, scripturę recitentur.»

Inculcas postea nescio quam christianam modestiam, cui haud absimile est, quod Lutheranorum convitia nobis imputas. Et quid hic possumus tibi, mi Christophyle, respondere, nisi quod Paulus Timotheo suo praecipit dicens: «Predica sermonem, insta tempestive, intempestive, argue, increpa, exhortare cum omni lenitate et doctrina!» Sic et Baptistam, Christum ipsum, Petrum et Paulum paulo amariores fuisse videmus, quoties reiecto dei verbo hypocritę palliatam tentabant agere comoediam. Scimus etiam nos infirmos iuxta apostoli pręceptum suscipiendos cum lenitate, verum infirmos in fide, non palam impios et veritatis impugnatores, qui ut plane deserendi sunt, ita a Christi plebe, si subversores esse perrexerint, verbo abigendi: 1. Timoth. 1 [20]; Tit. 1 [10ff]. Eius generis plurima sunt prophetarum paradigmata. Sed heus tu, ubi nunc Hieronymus tuus? Ubi Origenes? Ubi Augustinus? Scilicet illi adversariis suis permisere, ut quod libebat, liceret? Ergo quis ille Ruffinus, quis ille Celsus, Faustus et Julianus, in quos tanto stomacho invehuntur patres sanctissimi? Hec non dicimus, quod calumnię patrocinium nobis susceperimus, qua nihil perinde virulentum, impium minusque christianum, sed quod calumniam esse negamus, quoties zelo dei et populi commodo perversoribus resistitur calamo, ore, factis.

Quod si tu in docentibus vitam potius intueris quam doctrinam, vide, ne tibi usuveniat quod Barnabę accidisse constat, qui, cum Petri mores magis observaret quam doctrinam, in tantam incidit hypocrisim, ut Paulo liberatore opus haberet. Notissimus est locus Galath. 2 [13ff]. Aut quid tandem causę, quod dominus pharizęos audiri iubet, imitari vero prohibet? Quid? An falsa vult audiri dominus? An bona operantes sequi inhibet? Fieri ergo potest, ut mali opere, boni sint doctrina. Quid? An tu repudiares veritatem etiam a troglodyta oblatam? Haud puto. Itaque quis cogit, ut mentientibus credatis? Quoties inculcare oportet? Si vera dicimus, aequum est, ut veritati credatis, sin secus, deflectite! Porro vera sunt, quae docent scripturae, falsa, quae praeter hanc [!] produntur; haec coacti. Cęterum non negamus quemlibet vere christianum id exprimere factis, quod facilius quidem explicat verbis.</input>
  <output>English:
Christophylo Stiltzio.

Grace and peace from the Lord through Christ.

Your letter has been received with such favor that we felt the need to respond with a pamphlet instead, so that you cannot accuse us of total silence and laziness. But I know that you have already looked at me and John with a stern gaze, blaming us for our rashness. But please be more lenient; John would rather respond through me than take on this entire burden alone. For my part, I will only say that I wanted to reciprocate your blessing to me with a willingness to show you that it was most pleasant to me. So, Christophylo, our beloved friend, accept our response in both our names.

We do not despise anyone, since all must stand or fall before our common Lord, and no one comes to this doctrine of God unless the Father draws them. We rely on no help from outside, but rather attempt to eat a meal prepared by God rather than by men. We promise nothing extraordinary about ourselves, but we are certain that the doctrine taken from the law, the prophets, and the apostles, and preached in our own time, cannot be false, since it is not false that the heavens will never fall. We claim nothing more for ourselves than do the faithful, including your own and even our own Ambrose, who said, "Let us not be believed, but rather let the scriptures be read."

You then urge us to some kind of Christian modesty, which you also attribute to Lutheran insults. And what can we say to you, my Christophylo, except for what Paul commanded to his Timothy: "Preach the sermon, be persistent in season and out of season, rebuke, correct, and encourage with all gentleness and doctrine!" So also we see that John the Baptist, Christ Himself, Peter, and Paul were sometimes a little more harsh when they rejected the word of God and tried to act in a hypocritical way. We know that we must receive the weak in faith according to the Apostle's command, but not open sinners and opponents of the truth, who should be abandoned if they become subverters, and who should be expelled from the flock of Christ with the word [1 Timothy 1:20; Titus 1:10ff]. There are many examples of this in the prophets. But where is your Jerome now? Where is Origen? Where is Augustine? Have they granted their opponents permission to do as they please? Who then is this Ruffinus, this Celsus, Faustus, and Julian, whom the most holy Fathers attack with such vehemence? We do not say this to give a place to slander, since nothing is as virulent, impious, and un-Christian, but we deny that this is slander when the pen, the mouth, and the deed oppose those who reject the word of God and the advantage of the people.

If you look at the lives of teachers rather than their doctrine, be careful that you do not suffer what happened to Barnabas, who, when he observed Peter's behavior more than his doctrine, fell into such hypocrisy that he needed to be freed by Paul. We all know the passage in Galatians 2:13ff. Or what is the reason that the Lord orders the Pharisees to be heard, but forbids them to be imitated? What? Does the Lord want to hear lies? Does He forbid us to follow those who do good? Is it possible for someone to be bad in their deeds but good in their doctrine? Or would you reject the truth even if it were offered by a barbarian? I don't think so. So who forces you to believe liars? How often must it be inculcated? If we are speaking the truth, it is fair that you believe it; if not, turn away! Moreover, the scriptures teach the truth, and what is said outside of this is forced. But we do not deny that the truly Christian can express in works what is more easily expressed in words.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Tun' autem ille, qui nos alterius domini servos iudicas? Tun', qui crimina fratribus impingis? Nam sic scribis: «Vos vero non facta Christo digna, sed fidem nescio qualem etiam sine operibus praefigitis.» Heccine tua christiana modestia? Eos nempe, qui charitati student et innocentiae (quantum datur, neque enim quis unquam subito aethera petit) gentilitatis adcusare? Bona verba queso. Nam facta Christo indigna quid aliud sunt quam filiorum in tenebris versantium fructus? Et si ignoras, legeEphes. 4 [17ff] et 5 [8ff], 1. Ioan. 2 [9ff] et Roma. 1 [18ff]. O ergo et o miseras animas nostras, si tam temerario cogerentur subiacere iuditio! Du tibi tuam dant [!] mentem. Et qualem, oro, fidem praefigimus? Videor propemodum videre, quod etiamdum ignores, quid de fide et operibus sentiamus. Paucis ergo accipe et ab intollerandis abstine scomatis. Fidem adserimus unctionem esse a deo, qua certificantur de ea salute fideles, quam per Christum consequti sunt. Cuius officium, conditio et genius sit: pacificare cor, iustificare et bonos procreare fructus, non quidem eos, qui quicquam ad iustificationem conferant, quando sola fides per sese est absoluta iustificatio, sed qui a providentia sint necessarii. Quae omnia d[ivus] apostolus sic docuit Ephes. 1 [4ff] et 2 [8ff], Roma. 4 [1ff], 3 [21ff], 10 [4ff], Gala. 3 [1ff], 2 [15ff]. Sed brevia fortassis malles, ergo accipe. Nihil pacificat cor nisi sola fides, ergo nihil iustificat nisi sola fides. Antecessio scripturę est Isaię 57 [15ff], Acto. 15 [8f], Roma. 5 [1f], Galat. 3 [1ff], Ebręos 9 [14]. Progressus vero hinc fulscitur [!], quod iustitia aliud non sit quam cordis pax et vita: Galat. 2 [19f]; 1. Ioan. 5 [11 ff]. Iterum: omni testamento confirmato nihil debet adiici, nihil demi, modo Pauli verbis credamus, Galat. 3 [15]. Cum vero testamento nobis semen unicum delegatum sit, in quo consequamur benedictionem, eaque in multis non sit constituta, Genes. 22 [16ff], Galat. 3 [15ff], quis non videt immotam stare sententiam: unicum Christum unicum esse humani generis iustitiam, quae in nullo praeterea semine constituta, sola fide nobiscum communicetur? Quod si dubitas, lege Ioan. 1 [18], 3 [13ff], 6 [46], 12 [44ff], Roma. 3 [21ff]. Rursus: fieri non potest, ut operibus ex officio et necessitate factis ulla debeatur merces aut iustificatio: Luce 17 [10]; Roma. 4 [2ff]. Atqui omnia christianorum opera ex officio et ea necessitate fiunt, qua deus omnia ab aeterno disponit, Ephes. 2 [10]; proinde fieri non potest, ut operibus ulla debeatur iustitia. Imo nos ipsi fidem a spe et charitate non sęparamus [!], nisi qua una latius altera patet. Ergo quid scripturarum locis opus apud eos, qui bona opera non negant, imo exigunt? Tamen iis iustificationem non tribuunt, ne inanis fiat cruor Christi: Galat. 2 [21]. Precamur autem deum optimum maximum, ut ita nostrorum episcoporum mores corrigat, ne nimis crebro ex fructibus lupos sentiamus, tribuatque omnibus ex aequo evangelion profitentibus, ut inculpati luminaria sint mundi et tales, quales omnino episcopos vult esse apostolus.

De coniugio meo sic scribis: «Non improbo, quod uxorem duxeris, sed quod sic duxeris, ut ipsi adhereas, Christum vero dimittas». Audi ergo quid tibi respondeat apostolus: «Hoc autem ad id», inquit, «quod vobis conducibile est, dico, non uti laqueum vobis iniiciam, sed ut quod honestum ac decorum est sequamini et adhereatis domino absque ulla distractione». Ecce, quanto acumine apostolus totam disputationem in pauca coniiciat capita, vultque huc omnes consilii nervös tendi, ut sic rem agamus, ut absque ulla distractione adhereamus Domino. Iam cum nulli magis a domino avelluntur, quam quos urunt carnis flammae, existimavi me deo posse adglutinari fortius, si illas extinguerem connubio, quas alias non poteram nisi gravi offensione dei restinguere; nam ut «honorabile est inter omnes connubium et cubile impollutum», ita «adulteros et scortatores iudicabit deus».

Iam quae de sacrificio missae scripsisti, haud mediocri gaudio nos refocillarunt, eo quod e pernicioso errore liberatum vidimus et proinde hoc argumento te instructiorem fieri cupimus. In omni sacrifitio, quod peccata antiquare debet, necesse est, ut sanguis fundatur, quia «sine sanguinis effusione non fit remissio»: Ebrae. 9 [22]. Atqui in missa, quae pro expiatione vivorum et mortuorum hactenus divendita est, sanguis non funditur, quando sanguis Christi semel effusus semper sufficit ad omnium omnia tollenda peccata: Ephe. 1 [7]; Galat. 1 [4]; Coll. 1 [14]; Ebrae. 10 [11ff]. Itaque fieri non potest, ut missa sit sacrificium.</input>
  <output>Sed si sacrificium non est, quid est? Laudatio et gratulatio Deo exhibitio pro redemptione, quam Christus per suum sanguinem nobis acquisivit: Ephe. 5 [2]; Col. 3 [16]; Ebr. 13 [15].

Who then are you, who judges us servants of another Lord? Who accuses his brothers of guilt? For you write thus: “But you set forth a faith I know not what, even without works.” Is this your Christian modesty? To accuse those who labor for charity and innocence (as much as it is possible, for no one can suddenly reach the heavens)? Please, use good words. For what are works not worthy of Christ, but the fruits of those who wallow in darkness? And if you don’t know, read Ephesians 4 [17ff] and 5 [8ff], 1 John 2 [9ff] and Romans 1 [18ff]. Ah, and alas for our souls, if they were compelled to submit to such rash judgment! Take to yourself your own mind. And what sort of faith do we set forth, I ask? I almost see that you still do not know what we think of faith and works. Well then, receive these few things and abstain from unbearable scoffs. We affirm that faith is an anointing from God, by which the faithful are assured of that salvation which they have obtained through Christ. Its office, condition, and character is to pacify the heart, to justify, and to produce good fruits, not those which contribute anything to justification, since faith of itself is a complete justification, but those which are necessary according to the providence of God. All these things the blessed Apostle teaches in Ephesians 1 [4ff] and 2 [8ff], Romans 4 [1ff], 3 [21ff], 10 [4ff], Galatians 3 [1ff], 2 [15ff]. But perhaps you would rather have something brief, so receive this. Nothing pacifies the heart but faith alone, and therefore nothing justifies but faith alone. The precedent of Scripture is in Isaiah 57 [15ff], Acts 15 [8f], Romans 5 [1f], Galatians 3 [1ff], Hebrews 9 [14]. The progress thence follows, that righteousness is nothing else but peace and life of the heart: Galatians 2 [19f]; 1 John 5 [11 ff]. Again, nothing must be added to or taken away from any established testament, if we believe the words of Paul, Galatians 3 [15]. But since a single seed is appointed us by the testament, by which we obtain the blessing, and that is not established in many, Genesis 22 [16ff], Galatians 3 [15ff], who does not see that the sentence must remain unshaken, that Christ alone is the righteousness of the human race, which is not constituted in any other seed, but is communicated to us by faith alone? And if you doubt, read John 1 [18], 3 [13ff], 6 [46], 12 [44ff], Romans 3 [21ff]. Again, it is impossible that any reward or justification should be due to works done by duty and necessity: Luke 17 [10]; Romans 4 [2ff]. But all the works of Christians are done by duty and that necessity by which God has disposed all things from eternity, Ephesians 2 [10]; therefore it is impossible that any justification should be due to works. Nor do we separate faith from hope and charity, except that one is wider than the other. Then what need is there of places of Scripture among those who do not deny good works, but indeed require them, yet do not grant justification to them, lest the blood of Christ be made of none effect: Galatians 2 [21]. We pray to God the best and greatest, that he may so correct the manners of our bishops, that we may not too often perceive wolves among the fruits, and that he grant to all who profess the Gospel to be equally without blame, that they may be lights of the world, and such as the Apostle would have all bishops to be.

You write of my marriage thus: “I do not disapprove that you have taken a wife, but that you have done so, adhering to her, and leaving Christ.” Hear then what the Apostle answers thee: “But I speak this,” says he, “concerning that which is fitting and seemly, not that I may put a yoke upon you, but that ye may follow that which is honest and honorable, and may cleave to the Lord without any distraction.” Behold, with what acuteness the Apostle compacts the whole dispute into a few heads, and would have all the strings of counsel to be bent this way, that we may so act that we may adhere to the Lord without any distraction. Now no persons are sooner torn from the Lord than those who are burnt with the flames of flesh, and I judged that I could be more firmly glued to God, if I extinguished those by marriage, which else I could not quench but with great offence of God; for as “it is honorable among all to have matrimony, and the bed undefiled,” so “God will judge adulterers and whoremongers.”

Now what you have written concerning the Mass has refreshed us with no small joy, in that we have seen you delivered from a pernicious error, and therefore we desire that you may be the better instructed by this argument. In every sacrifice which ought to remit sins, there must be the shedding of blood, because “without the shedding of blood there is no remission”: Hebrews 9 [22]. But in the Mass, which has been used heretofore for the expiation of the living and the dead, there is no shedding of blood, since the blood of Christ, once shed, is always sufficient to take away all sins of all men: Ephesians 1 [7]; Galatians 1 [4]; Colossians 1 [14]; Hebrews 10 [11ff]. Therefore it is impossible that the Mass should be a sacrifice. But if it is not a sacrifice, what is it? A praise and thanksgiving to God for the redemption which Christ has acquired for us by his blood: Ephesians 5 [2]; Colossians 3 [16]; Hebrews 13 [15].</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="3">
  <input>Sed in hoc etiamdum hallucinaris, quod me ad praecularum sacrificium adigere videris. Fateor inter christianos unicam esse hostiam, nempe labiorum vitulos ac corporis mactationem: Oseę 14 [2]; Psal. 39 [40,6ff]; 49 [50, 14]; Roma. 12 [1f]; Ebrę. 13 [15]. At quis est, qui ignoret omnes ex aequo christianos iuxta hoc sacrifitium esse sacerdotes? Consule textum Exod. 19 [6], Isaie 61 [6], 66 [20ff], 1. Petri 2 [9]. Quae ergo religio, sub praetextu longe precationis et sacrificii peculiaris domos vorare viduarum? Quasi scilicet melius esset sacrifici uncti et rasi, imo palliati sacrificium, et non potius hoc melius, quod ardentius. Scripturę iuditium istoc est. Non est ergo, quod Lutherum aliud sentientem aut Rütlingii illius impietatem nobis obiicias. Quid ad Christum, quod Origenes idem olim cum Rütlingio nebulone sentiebat? Ergo ne fides in Christum vana, quia Sabellius et Valentinus de Christo male sentiebant? Imo quid ad fideles, quod Pomeranus, Zuinglius, Lutherus, Oecolampadius, Regius et Fabritius dissentiunt? Utpote qui personam non respiciunt, 1. Cor. 3 [5ff], 4 [1ff], quique indubie norunt, quod hereses esse oporteat, nimirum ut probentur probatiores: 1. Cor. 11 [19]. An nescis omnem carnem esse foenum, at solum domini verbum manere in ęternum?

In rupem ergo cum enavigaverimus sacraque ancora navis stet pacta, nihil est, quod a verbo dei nos avellere possit, et si totus doctorum cohors recideret, etsi totus tumultuaretur orbis; adeo, mi Christophyle, frustraneae sunt tuae ironiae. Tu quiritaris: «Ubi nunc scriptura facilis?» - At regius propheta canit: «Lex domini immaculata, convertens animam; testimonium domini fidele, sapientiam praestans parvulo». «Lucerna pedi meo verbum tuum et lumen semite meae». Et Petrus lucernam vocat propheticam scripturam; igitur quid de apostolica dicimus? Tu subdis: «Quam vel idiotae intelligere debent.» At Christus, humani generis salus perorat: «Gratias ago tibi, pater, quod absconderis hec a sapientibus et prudentibus, et revelaveris ea parvulis». Quae alias in Corinthiis dilucidissima erunt: 1. Cor. 1 [18ff] et 2 [10ff]. Quid, quod alibi sic pronunciat Paulus: «Quod si adhuc velatum sive obscurum est evangelion nostrum, in his, qui pereunt, velatum est; in quibus deus huius seculi excaecavit sensus incredulorum, ne illucesceret illis lumen evangelii»?

Post multa tandem exigis a me scripturas, conquereris, quod Erasmi libellum de impietate nondum convicerim; ex quibus facile subodorare potui, quod ea non observaveris oculatius, quae de providentia dei in transcursu scripsimus, nam certa, aliis occupatissimi, dare nequivimus putavimusque ista sufficere docto. Dabimus ergo scripturas, sed et has obiter. Sic scriptum est: «Per deum vivimus, movemur et sumus». Constat ergo, quod dei potentia omnia ordiantur,, fiant et finiantur. Id quod alibi sic scribitur: «Ex deo et per illum et in illum omnia. Ipsi gloria!» Cui etiam subscribit sapientissimus prophetarum Moses Deutro. 31 [6ff], regius propheta David Psal. 103 [104,1ff] et apostolica ecclesia Actor. 4 [24ff]. Is porro, qui divinae detrahit operationi ac potentiae, is ne pius, an impius? Et qui homini per liberum arbitrium tribuit quod dei est, an ne is divinae detrahit operationi et potentiae? Adde quod scriptum est: «In manu enim illius et nos et sermones nostri et omnis sapientia et operum scientiae disciplina».

Et «deus est, qui agit in vobis et ut velitis, et ut efficiatis». Et clarius: «Non sumus eidonei ex nobis ipsis cogitare quicquam, tanquam ex nobis ipsis, sed omnis promptitudo nostra ex deo est». Quis ergo ille, qui liberum arbitrium homini tribuat? Salus enim non in nostris, sed illius manibus est: Ioan. 10 [28f]. Ille trahit quem vult et indurat quem vult: Ioan. 6 [44]; Roma. 9 [18]; Isaię 45 [7]. Et intellectus hominis nihil sapit nisi carnalia, eadem meditatur et voluntas: Roma. 7 [14ff]; 1. Cor. 2 [6ff]; Ephe. 2 [3]. Propterea ait Paulus: «Haec inter se mutuo adversantur» (caro et spiritus), «ut non quęcumque volueritis, eadem faciatis». His adiunge historiam Bileam in Numeris Mosaicis. Corpus denique non rapitur sua voluntate: Math. 5 [29ff]; 6 [25ff]; 10 [17ff]. Consule Psal. 38 [1 ff] et in summa Roma. 8 [3ff], 9 [11ff]. Alias sic clauditur: «In Christo sumus praedestinati secundum propositum illius, cuius vi hunt universa, iuxta decretum voluntatis ipsius».</input>
  <output>You seem to still be hallucinating that you are forcing me to make pagan sacrifices. I confess that among Christians there is only one sacrifice, namely the sacrifice of the lips and the slaughter of the body: Hos. 14 [2]; Ps. 39 [40,6ff]; 49 [50, 14]; Rom. 12 [1f]; Heb. 13 [15]. But who is unaware that all Christians are equally priests according to this sacrifice? Consult Exod. 19 [6], Is. 61 [6], 66 [20ff], 1 Pet. 2 [9]. So what religion would ravage the homes of widows under the pretext of a far-reaching prayer and a particular sacrifice? As if it were better to offer sacrifices anointed and shaven, indeed clothed, than this, which is better and more ardent. The judgement of Scripture is this. Therefore there is no need to object to us Luther's different opinion or the impiety of that Röttinger. What does it have to do with Christ that Origen once had the same opinion as Röttinger the fool? Therefore, is faith in Christ vain because Sabellius and Valentinus had a bad opinion of Christ? Indeed, what does it have to do with the faithful that Pomeranus, Zwingli, Luther, Oecolampadius, Regius, and Fabritius differ? As they do not regard person, 1 Cor. 3 [5ff], 4 [1ff], and who undoubtedly know that there should be heresies, namely, in order to prove those who are approved: 1 Cor. 11 [19]. Do you not know that all flesh is grass, and only the Lord's word remains forever?

Therefore, when we have sailed into the rock and the sacred anchor of the ship has been set in place, nothing can take us away from the word of God, and if the whole band of teachers fell away and the whole world was stirred up; so, my Christian, your ironies are in vain. You complain: "Where now is the easy Scripture?" - But the royal prophet sings: "The law of the Lord is immaculate, converting the soul; the testimony of the Lord is faithful, giving wisdom to the little one". "Your word is a lamp to my feet and a light to my path". And Peter calls the prophetic Scripture a lamp; so what do we say about the apostolic? You add: "Which even idiots should understand." But Christ, the salvation of the human race, proclaimed: "I thank you, Father, that you have hidden these things from the wise and prudent and revealed them to the little ones". Which will be very clear elsewhere in the Corinthians: 1 Cor. 1 [18ff] and 2 [10ff]. What, that elsewhere Paul so pronounces: "If the gospel of us is still veiled or obscure, it is veiled in those who perish, in whom the god of this age has blinded the minds of the unbelievers, so that the light of the gospel would not shine on them"?

Finally, after many things, you ask me for Scriptures, you complain that I have not yet refuted Erasmus' book on impiety; from which I could easily perceive that you had not observed them more carefully, what we had written about the providence of God in passing, since we were unable to give certain things, being very busy, and we thought that this would suffice for the learned. We will therefore give Scriptures, but also incidentally. So it is written: "We live, move, and are through God". Therefore it is certain that all things are ordered, made, and ended by the power of God. Which is written elsewhere in this way: "From God and through him and in him are all things. To him be the glory! "To which even the wisest of the prophets, Moses, subscribes Deut. 31 [6ff], the royal prophet David Ps. 103 [104,1ff] and the apostolic church Act. 4 [24ff]. He who detracts from the divine operation and power, is he pious or impious? And he who gives man free will what is God's, does he not detract from the divine operation and power? Add that it is written: "For it is in his hand that we and our words and all wisdom and knowledge of works are".

And "it is God who works in you both to will and to do". And more clearly: "We are not able to think of anything from ourselves, as from ourselves, but all our readiness is from God". Who then is he who gives man free will? For salvation is in his hands, not in ours: John 10 [28f]. He draws whom he will and hardens whom he will: John 6 [44]; Rom. 9 [18]; Is. 45 [7]. And the understanding of man tastes nothing but carnal things, meditates on the same things and wills: Rom. 7 [14ff]; 1 Cor. 2 [6ff]; Ephe. 2 [3]. Therefore Paul says: "These things are opposed to each other" (flesh and spirit), "so that you do not do whatever you want". Add to this the story of Balaam in the Mosaic Numbers. Finally, the body is not taken by its own will: Math. 5 [29ff]; 6 [25ff]; 10 [17ff]. Consult Ps. 38 [1 ff] and in sum Romans 8 [3ff], 9 [11ff]. Elsewhere it is closed in this way: "We are predestined in Christ according to his purpose, by whose power all things are done according to the decree of his will".</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="4">
  <input>Quare iterum ingero: «Si providentia est, liberum arbitrium non est; alias enim providentia non esset providentia. Si porro liberum arbitrium, iam non est providentia; alias enim liberum arbitrium non erit liberum arbitrium.» Sed de his satis. Habes, ni fallor, scripturas, habes hominis impietatem, elapsam verius quam excogitatam. Neque enim adeo ingratus sum erga bene merentes, ut alias in eos excandere soleo, qui deo detrahunt et virium nostrarum pomeria ultra legem dei prorogant. In pręsentiarum copiosiora dare non licuit, utpote qui stilum assidue, ut pręcaris, in gloriam Christi exerceam; si modo eam intelligas, qua credimus et confitemur, quod solus Christus «nobis datus sit a patre sapientia iustitiaque, sanctificatio et redemptio».

Rogas deinde, et cur eos non contemnam, qui sine scriptura novos ritus in eucharistiae negocio invehant, cuiusmodi sit Zuinglius noster. Sed age, sit noster, quando est christianus! Interim quid respondeamus, animadverte. Qui adserit panem eucharistiae et vinum poculi aliud non esse quam panem et vinum, porro Christi corpus sedere ad dexteram patris, is docet quod omnis docuit primitiva ecclesia, scriptura sancta et fides catholica. Qui vero impanatum deum praedicat, is demum adfert quod nullae admittunt scripturae quodque haeresibus complurimis confine est. Nobis non credatur, veritas audiatur, quam tu nobis non deesse experieris. Et tota questio in hoc ceu cardine volvitur num hęc particula «est» per divinam effecerit potentiam, ut panis in corpus Christi et vinum transierit in sanguinem. Investigandum ergo ante omnia, quale sit corpus Christi, quis sanquis, de quo hic loqutus sit Christus; deinde num hoc edi possit aut bibi, hoc est, num huius loci sana intelligentia convinci id possit, quod de naturali corpore et sanguine hactenus tradidistis. Imprimis nemini dubium, quin corpus Christi certa sit substantia, visibilis, humanam habens dimmensionem [!], sive quantitatem spectes sive gravedinem, adeoque quod nihil a nostro corpore, carnibus, nervis et ossibus compacto, dissideat, nisi qua labe caret. Nam sic scribit apostolus: «Posteaquam ergo pueri commertium habent cum carne et sanguine, et ipse similiter particeps factus est eorundem. Non enim videlicet angelos adsumit, sed semen Abrahę adsumit» etc. Hinc fit, ut esuriat, sitiat, algeat, dolore torqueatur refocilleturque gaudio. Cetera, que de hoc dici possunt, tractabimus et in sequentibus. Nunc vero videamus, num de hoc corpore loquatur Christus. Dicit autem: «Hoc est corpus meum, quod pro vobis tradetur.» Ergo is, qui deus fuit, passus est secundum eam naturam, quam adsumpsit. Sic enim Petrus: «Cum igitur Christus», inquit, «passus sit pro nobis carne» etc. Corpus ergo visibile ac naturale est pro nobis traditum, et non spirituale, non glorificatum. De visibili, inquam, et quantitativo (ut ita loquar) dicit Christus: «Et hic murus ahaeneus esto.» Iam si illa particula «est» metamorphosin causatur, omnino necessarium est, ut panis in id transmutetur corpus, cuius facit mentionem. At naturalis et visibilis mentionem facit, quorum nihil in pane videmus, insuper quod edi non potest, quemadmodum ipse iussit, ut porrectum manducaremus; imo si posset, commestum [!] tamen non prodesset: Ioan. 6.

Si responderis: corpus Christi manducandum in spiritu, assentior; verum quid istud huc facit, cum de spirituali manducatione hoc loci nihil agatur? Nam si de ea hic loquitur, ergo et Christus passus erit in spiritu, hoc est in phantasmate. Subdit enim: «Hoc est corpus meum, quod pro vobis traditur» [Lk 22,19; 1 Kor 11,24]. Verum id olim a proceribus ecclesiasticis ceu sesquihęreticum adversus Martionem et innumeras alias hęreticorum phalanges proscriptum est. Ut nunc non adferam, quod «spiritus carnem et ossa non habet» et Christus sola fide manducetur. Quod si mihi non credis, crede vel ipso Christo, Ioan. 6[35], et patribus tuis: Augustino, Ireneo, Tertulliano et Ambrosio. His accedit, quod unica est persona Christi, quam vos corporali vestra praesentia integra in singulis ecclesiarum panibus confunditis, more Nestorii et Aetianorum, et quod ipsa docet fides humanam naturam sedere ad dexteram patris, unde non moveatur nisi ad iuditii diem: Actor. 1 [9ff]; 3 [19ff]; Ebrae. 10 [12].

Cui sic subscribit Ambrosius, «De incarnationis mysterio» ca. 5: «Non enim inter homines caro eius, quia secundum carnem iam non novimus Christum. Terra dicit: Non est mecum, quia resurrexit. Denique angelus ait: «Quid queritis viventem cum mortuis?» [Lk 24,5].» Augustinus in Joan. cap. 6 sic:</input>
  <output>«Sed hic est panis, qui de caelo descendit. Quomodo descendit, nisi quod ipsa veritas descendit? Quomodo manducatur, nisi quod credendo, intelligendo, amando manducatur?»

Answer: I raise the question again: "If there is Providence, there is no free will; otherwise Providence would not be Providence. If, on the other hand, there is free will, there is no longer Providence; otherwise, free will would not be free will." But enough of that. You have, if I'm not mistaken, the scriptures, you have the impiety of mankind, rather fallen than devised. Nor am I so ungrateful to those who have deserved well of me, as I am wont to be to those who detract from God and extend the boundaries of our powers beyond the law of God. I was not able to give more in the present, since I constantly exercise my style, as is fitting, to the glory of Christ; provided you understand that faith which we profess and believe, that Christ alone has been given to us by the Father as wisdom, justice, sanctification, and redemption."

You then ask, and why do I not despise those who, without Scripture, introduce new rites into the matter of the Eucharist, such as our Zwingli. But come, let him be ours, since he is a Christian! Meanwhile, consider what we should answer. He who maintains that the bread of the Eucharist and the wine of the cup are nothing else but bread and wine, and that in addition the body of Christ sits at the right hand of the Father, teaches what has been taught by all the primitive Church, by the Holy Scripture, and by the Catholic faith. But he who preaches an impanate God brings forward something which is not admitted by any Scripture, and is adjacent to many heresies. Let not us be believed, but let the truth be heard, which you have not found to be wanting in us. And the whole question revolves around this hinge, whether this particle "is" effected by divine power, so that the bread is changed into the body of Christ and the wine into his blood. It is therefore to be inquired before all, what is the body of Christ, what is his blood, of which Christ speaks here; and afterwards, whether this can be eaten or drunk, that is, whether it can be proved by a sound interpretation of this place, what has heretofore been delivered concerning the natural body and blood. Above all, no one doubts that the body of Christ is a certain substance, visible, having a human dimension [!], whether you consider quantity or gravity, and thus nothing is different from our body, compacted of flesh, nerves, and bones, except that it is free from any blemish. For thus the apostle writes: "Forasmuch then as the children are partakers of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise took part of the same" [Heb 2:14]. Hence it follows that he hungers, thirsts, feels cold, is tormented with pain, and rejoices with joy. The rest which can be said of this, we shall treat in the following. But now let us see if Christ speaks here of this body. He says: "This is my body, which is given for you" [Lk 22:19; 1 Cor 11:24]. Therefore he who was God suffered according to that nature which he had assumed. Thus Peter says: "Forasmuch then as Christ suffered for us in the flesh" [1 Pet 4:1]. The visible and natural body was therefore given for us, and not a spiritual or glorified one. Of the visible, I say, and the quantified (so to speak) Christ says: "And this is to be a strong wall" [Song 8:9]. Now if that particle "is" causes a metamorphosis, it is absolutely necessary that the bread should be changed into that body of which he makes mention. But he makes mention of a natural and visible one, of which we see nothing in the bread; besides which it cannot be eaten, as he commanded that it should be given to us and eaten; nay, if it could, yet its being eaten would not be of any benefit: John 6 [35].

If you answer that the body of Christ is to be eaten in spirit, I assent; but what has this to do here, since nothing is here spoken of a spiritual eating? For if he speaks here of it, then Christ also suffered in spirit, that is, in phantasm. For he subjoins: "This is my body which is given for you" [Lk 22:19; 1 Cor 11:24]. But this was long ago condemned by the chief of the Church as sesqui-heretical against Marcion and innumerable other swarms of heretics. That I may not now allege, that "the spirit has not flesh and bones" [Lk 24:39], and that Christ is to be eaten with only faith. But if you do not believe me, believe either Christ himself, John 6 [35], or your own fathers: Augustine, Ireneus, Tertullian, and Ambrose. To this is added, that there is one person of Christ, whom you confound in the whole bread of each Church with your corporal presence, after the manner of Nestorius and the Aetians; and that the faith itself teaches that the human nature sits at the right hand of the Father, whence it is not to be moved but at the day of judgment: Acts 1 [9ff]; 3 [19ff]; Heb. 10 [12].

To this Ambrose subscribes in "On the Mystery of the Incarnation" ch. 5: "For his flesh is not among men, since we know Christ now no more according to the flesh. The earth says, 'He is not here;' for he is risen. Finally, the angel says, 'Why seek ye the living among the dead?'" [Lk 24:5]. Augustine in John ch. 6 thus: "But this is the bread which came down from heaven. How did it come down, but that the very truth came down? How is it eaten, but that it is eaten by believing, understanding, and loving?</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="5">
  <input>«Corpus enim Christi in uno loco sit oportet, veritas autem illius ubique diffunditur». Docuit autem in praecedentibus locum illum esse dexteram patris. Tertullianus vero in libro de resurrectione carnis sic: «In regia coelorum sedet adhuc Iesus ad dexteram patris, homo, etsi deus, caro et sanguis, etsi nostris puriora, idem tamen et substantia et forma, qua ascendit, talis etiam descensurus, ut angeli adfirmant, agnoscendis scilicet eis, qui illum convulneraverunt. Hic sequester dei atque hominum appellatus ex utriusque partis deposito commisso sibi, carnis quoque depositum servat in semetipso, arrabonem summę totius. Quemadmodum enim nobis arrabonem spiritus reliquit, ita et a nobis arrabonem carnis accepit et vexit in coelum pignus totius summae illuc quandoque redigende» etc. Hec ille. Ecce, quid poterat dici adpertius? Ecce, ut carnalis vestra praesentia amabile foedus et dulcia obnubilet pignora: «Sed Christus deus, et proinde in omnibus locis integer esse potest.» - Respondeo: Imprimis incurris eidololatriae scelus, nam si in multis locis integer est, ergo multi sunt dii, contra articulum fidei: «Credo in unum deum.» Una enim vis dei, quae gloria sua totum terrarum orbem spherasque adimplet coelestes; quae si integra in variis esset locis, quivis locus integrum haberet deum pluralitate distantem. Deinde naturas in Christo confundis more Thimotii et Apollinaris, nam tribuis divinitatis proprium humanitati. Contra quod sic scribit Ambrosius in eo libro, quod paulo ante citavimus, eodem cap.: «Ergo splendori gloriae non permisceas attramentum [!] naturae.» Et Tertullianus «Adversus Praxeam» apertius: «Videmus», inquit, «duplicem statum non confusum, sed coniunctum in una persona deum et hominem Iesum. De Christo autem dissero; et adeo salva est utriusque proprietas substantiae, ut et spiritus res suas egerit in illo, et caro passiones suas functa sit» etc. Vide et Ambros[ium], superioris libri cap. 6. Propterea cum dicis divinitatem ubique esse posse et mox ingeris: «ergo et corpus», videsne, quod naturarum sive substantiarum proprietates confudisti et humanitati tribuisti quod divinitatis proprium erat? Nos confitemur unam esse Christi personam, in qua duae naturae, quodque iuxta divinam praesens sit in omnibus locis, porro iuxta humanam sedeat ad dexteram patris, verus deus et homo. Vide «Definitiones ecclesiasticas» cap. 2, et De consecra[tione], distinc[tione] 2, cano[ne] «Prima quidem».

Sed quorsum haec? Omnia in hunc finem, ut doceamus ipsam rei conditionem ac fidem catholicam convincere, tropum subesse in verbo: «est», sive iam is metaphora sit sive metonymia. Voluit enim dominus indicare mysterium paschatos et abrogare agnum paschalem. Imprimis ergo edit cum discipulis pascha, deinde subdit se amodo ex eo non esurum, «donec compleatur in regno dei» [Lk 22,16]. Qui hębraismus aliud non sonat nisi hoc: In posterum de hoc agno non edam, neque vos ex eo edere volo, quia nunc adest regnum dei, in quo typo per me satisfit, qui verus agnus tollo peccata mundi omnemque sanguinem, meo sisto. Ideo significabat pascha Christum passurum, et esus eius memoriale erat. Proinde necessum erat, ut mutaret, ne passo Christo expectaretur signo docente passurus. Accipit ergo panem et iubet, ut edant loco agni paschalis in rei memoriam, quod Christus sit traditus pro humano genere, atque adeo, ut quemadmodum agnus significaverit Christum passurum, sic panis significet verum corpus illius veri agni, quod iam traditum sit. Sic enim subdit: «Hoc facite in mei memoriam» [Lk 22,19].

Iam vide, mi Christophyle, an non et Gregorius decreta et omnium veterum monimenta idem de hoc typo tradiderint, an non omnia probe cohereant, an non singula sint pientissima. Quod si tropum admittere nolumus, periculum erit, ne nos cogamur pateras, pocula et calices vorare. Nam eadem ratione dicit: «Hoc poculum est sanguis» [Lk 22,20]. Quomodo item Arrianis occurremus obiicientibus: «Pater maior me est» [Joh 14,28], nisi singula excusserimus, ut nos ante specimen eius rei in corporis tractatione exhibuimus?</input>
  <output>Translation: "It is necessary that the body of Christ be in one place, but his truth is spread everywhere". He taught in the previous passages that that place was the right hand of the Father. Tertullian, however, in his book on the resurrection of the flesh says this: "Jesus still sits in the royal heaven at the right hand of the Father, a man, although God, flesh and blood, although purer than ours, still the same in substance and form, as he ascended, so he will descend, as the angels affirm, to recognize those who wounded him. This mediator of God and men, called from both sides, the deposit entrusted to him, also preserves in himself the deposit of flesh, the pledge of the whole sum. For just as he left us a pledge of the Spirit, so he received from us a pledge of the flesh and took it to heaven, a pledge of the whole sum to be brought back there someday". This is what he said. Look, what could be said more clearly? Look, how may your carnal presence obscure the beloved covenant and sweet pledges: "But Christ is God, and therefore can be whole in all places". - I answer: First of all you are guilty of the sin of idolatry, for if he is whole in many places, then there are many gods, contrary to the article of faith: "I believe in one God". For there is one power of God, which fills the whole earth and the heavenly spheres with its glory; if it were whole in various places, each place would have a separate God with a plurality of differences. Secondly, you confuse the natures in Christ in the manner of Timothy and Apollinus, for you attribute to humanity that which is proper to divinity. Against this Ambrose writes in the same book which we cited a little earlier in the same chapter: "Do not mix the ink of nature with the splendour of glory". And Tertullian more clearly in "Against Praxeus": "We see," he says, "two states not confused, but united in one person, God and man, Jesus Christ. I am speaking of Christ; and so the property of both substances is saved, so that the Spirit may do its own things in him, and the flesh may perform its own sufferings". See also Ambrose, chapter 6 of the previous book. Therefore, when you say that divinity can be everywhere and then add "therefore also the body", do you see that you have confused the properties of natures or substances and attributed to humanity what was proper to divinity? We confess one person of Christ, in which there are two natures, and that, according to the divine, it is present in all places, and according to the human, it sits at the right hand of the Father, true God and man. See "Ecclesiastical Definitions" chapter 2, and On the Consecration, Distinction 2, Canon "First of all".

But what is the purpose of all this? Everything for this purpose, that we may teach that the very condition of the thing and the Catholic faith agrees, that there is a trope in the word "is", whether it be a metaphor or metonymy. For the Lord wanted to indicate the mystery of the Passover and to abolish the Passover lamb. First of all, he ate the Passover with the disciples, then he added that from now on he would not eat of it "until it is fulfilled in the kingdom of God" [Lk 22:16]. This Hebrewism means nothing else than this: From now on I will not eat of this lamb, nor do I want you to eat of it, because now the kingdom of God has come, in which I make satisfaction by myself, the true Lamb, who takes away the sins of the world and all the blood, and puts an end to me. Therefore, the Passover signified Christ to be suffered, and its eating was a memorial. Therefore it was necessary to change, lest Christ to be suffered should be expected by a sign teaching it. He therefore takes bread and commands that they should eat in place of the Passover lamb in memory of the thing, that Christ was delivered for the human race, and thus, as the lamb signified Christ to be suffered, so the bread should signify the true body of the true Lamb, which is now delivered. Thus he subjoins: "Do this in remembrance of me" [Lk 22:19].

Now see, my Christopher, whether Gregory and the monuments of all the ancients have not delivered the same thing about this type, whether all things do not cohere well, whether all things are not most pious. If we do not admit the trope, there will be danger lest we be forced to devour dishes, cups and chalices. For in the same way he says: "This cup is the blood" [Lk 22:20]. How will we answer the Arians who object: "My Father is greater than I" [John 14:28], unless we examine each thing, as we have shown before by a specimen of this thing in the handling of the body?</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="6">
  <input>Sed deo omnia possibilia? - Audio; sed idem praeter ordinem et decorum nihil facit, ut docuit etiam m[agister] in «Sententiis». - Sed vide Tectull[ianum] «Adversus Praxean». Verum credenda sunt, non curiosius perquirenda? - Sed dic, queso, an non «fides ex auditu, auditus per verbum dei»? Da ergo verbum fidei, quod tibi hanc praescribat! Respondes: «Hoc est corpus meum» [Lk 22,19 u. a.]. Interim vide, num ita sonent verba: «Accipite et credite, quod hoc sit corpus meum», an: «Accipite, edite hunc panem in eius rei symbolon, quod credatis corpus meum pro vobis traditum». Vide Basilium, De consecra[tione], distinc[tione]2, cano [ne]: «Timorem et fidem [!]». Docet ergo fides imprimis edere carnem, hoc est credere, quod caro Christi pro nobis caesa sit, deinde iubet etiam panem edere, quo me de eorum numero aliis prodo, qui se credunt morte Christi redemptos. Unde Paulus: «Probet seipsum homo, et deinde de pane edat et calice bibat» [1 Kor 11,28]. Quas manducationes cum scholastici, imprimis Aquinas cum suis, non observarunt, in hos Schytiae campos nos deduxere. Imo qui fieri posset, ut fidei loco id venderemus, quod ex diametro pugnat cum fidei articulis, quemadmodum superius ostendimus? Proinde fides haec parum distat ab ea, quam illi exigunt, qui curiosas artes exercent; cum christiana nihil aliud sit quam unctio sancta, corda de certissima salute certificans. Et dispeream, nisi innumerae heręses [!] sub hoc lateant deo triticeo!

Videndum iam, quis sit genius sanguinis Christi. Et principio, quemadmodum corpore nihil a nobis discrepavit Christus, sic neque sanguine, liquore, quo vegetantur artus, in quo etiam vivit anima. Is autem non effunditur ubilibet neque multoties, sed in passione tantum, quippe cum effusus semel semper sufficiat. Paulus, eius rei author sic docuit: «Habemus altare, de quo non est phas [!] edere his, qui tabernaculo deserviunt.» «Et Christus semel oblatus, ut multorum peccata tolleret, rursus absque peccato conspicietur his, qui eum expectant in salutem». Item: «Hic vero una pro peccatis oblata victima, perpetuo sedet ad dexteram dei. Unica enim oblatione perfectos effecit imperpetuum» etc. Nunc cum vinum toties sumatur et fundatur, nunc cum «Christus a mortuis resurrexit et amplius non moritur, mors illi ultra non dominetur», fieri non potest citra blasphemiam, ut vinum sit sanguis, convincitque denuo ipsa sanguinis Christi proprietas tropum in verbis Christi latere. Id quod ex verbis Paulinis potius quam nostris coniecturis patebit. Sic ergo Paulus eo loco, cui tu inniteris, 1. Cor. 11 [25]: «Hoc», inquit, «poculum novum testamentum est in meo sanguine.» Ante omnia vero constat, quod vinum non possit esse testamentum, sed potius sit sacramentum, imo testamenti symbolon. Similis locus est Genes. 17 [10ff], ubi dominus circumcisionem vocat pactum seu testamentum; cum tamen non esset testamentum, sed testamenti symbolon, ut ex ipsa verborum consequentia consequitur.

Et ne quid dubitare possis, animadverte. Unicum tantum in orbe testamentum est, quod ut ab initio fuit, sic nunquam abrogabitur. Testamentum sic habet: «Ero deus tuus et seminis tui, Abraham» [Gen 17,7]. «Ambula coram me et esto perfectus» [Gen 17,1]. «Patrem enim multarum gentium faciam te» [Gen 17,5], «et in semine tuo benedicentur omnes cognationes terre»: Genes. 12 [3]; 15 [5]; 17 [4ff]; 22 [18]. Porro quod id unicum sit et perpetuum, docent prophetae et apostoli Genes. 28 [4.13ff], Exod. 32 [13], Levitici 26 [42], Deutro. 4 [23.31], 4. Reg. 17 [2 Kön 17,13ff], 4. Ezrae 3 [15], Psal. 104 [105,8f], Isaie 51 [2], Math. 8 [11], Act. 3 [25], Roma. 4 [1ff], Gala. 3 [6ff] etc. Quibus consentiunt Tertullianus, «Adversus Martionem» lib. 4, Lactantius, lib. 4, cap. 20, et Augustinus in cap. 8. Ioannis; quibus manifestum fit, quod vinum non possit esse, nisi abusive, testamentum.</input>
  <output>Is it possible for God to do everything? - I hear; but He does nothing but is contrary to order and propriety, as is taught even by the Master in the 'Sentences'. - But see Tertullian's 'Against Praxeas.' Is it necessary to believe these things rather than to investigate them curiously? - But tell me, I pray you, is it not 'faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God'? Give, then, the word of faith which will prescribe this to you! You answer: 'This is my body' [Lk 22:19, etc.]. In the meantime, see whether the words are so expressed: 'Take and believe that this is my body', or 'Take, eat this bread in a symbol of the fact that you should believe that my body is given for you'. See Basil on the Consecration, Distinction and Canon: 'Fear and Faith!'. Therefore faith chiefly commands to eat the flesh, that is, to believe that the Christ's flesh was slain for us, and then orders to eat the bread, to the end that I should set myself apart from the number of those who believe themselves to be redeemed by the death of Christ. Wherefore Paul: 'Let a man prove himself, and then let him eat of that bread and drink of the cup' [1 Cor. 11:28]. Since the scholastics, principally Thomas with his followers, did not observe these eating, they have brought us into these Scythian fields. How could it even be thought of, that we should sell for a faith, that which is diametrically opposed to the articles of faith, as we have shown above? Hence this faith differs little from that which they demand, who exercise curious arts; whereas Christianity is nothing else than a holy unction, certifying hearts of the most certain salvation. And I shall be damned unless there be innumerable heresies under this chaff of wheat!

Now let us consider what is the genius of the blood of Christ. And in the first place, as Christ differed nothing from us in his body, so neither in his blood, the liquor by which the limbs are nourished, and in which the soul itself lives. This, however, is not shed every where, nor often, but only in his passion, since when it is once shed, it is enough for ever. Paul, the author of this matter, thus teaches: 'We have an altar, whereof they have no right to eat who serve the tabernacle'. 'And Christ being once offered to take away the sins of many, shall appear a second time, without sin, to them that look for him unto salvation'. Again: 'But this man, after he had offered one sacrifice for sins, for ever sat down on the right hand of God. For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified' etc. Now since the wine is taken and poured out so often, and since 'Christ is risen from the dead, and dies no more; death has no more dominion over him', it cannot be without blasphemy that the wine should be the blood; and again the very property of the blood of Christ convinces us that the trope is contained in the words of Christ. Which will appear rather from the words of Paul than from our own conjectures. Paul then in the place to which you appeal, 1 Cor. 11 [25], says: 'This cup is the new testament in my blood'. But before all things is it certain, that wine cannot be a testament, but rather a sacrament, yea, a symbol of a testament. A like place is Gen. 17 [10ff], where the Lord calls circumcision a covenant or testament; whereas yet it was not a testament, but a symbol of a testament, as is evident from the very consequent of the words.

And that you may not doubt of any thing, observe. There is but one testament in the world, which, as it was from the beginning, so it shall never be abrogated. This testament is thus: 'I will be thy God and the God of thy seed, Abraham' [Gen. 17:7]. 'Walk before me, and be perfect' [Gen. 17:1]. 'I will make thee a father of many nations' [Gen. 17:5], 'and in thy seed shall all the kindreds of the earth be blessed': Gen. 12 [3]; 15 [5]; 17 [4ff]; 22 [18]. Moreover, that this is the one and only and perpetual testament, the prophets and the apostles teach, Gen. 28 [4.13ff], Exod. 32 [13], Lev. 26 [42], Deut. 4 [23.31], 4 Kgs 17 [2 Kön 17:13ff], 4 Ezra 3 [15], Ps. 104 [105:8f], Is. 51 [2], Matt. 8 [11], Acts 3 [25], Rom. 4 [1ff], Gal. 3 [6ff] etc. To which agree Tertullian in 'Against Marrion' book 4, Lactantius book 4, chapter 20, and Augustine in chapter 8 of John; from which it is manifest that wine cannot be a testament, unless abusedly.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="7">
  <input>Cur ergo Christus novum vocat, si non interruptum? Primum, quia veteris typi omnes sunt hic adimpleti et in ipsa veritate nobis ostenduntur, quae illis contingebant in figura. Sic ubi novum, ibi antiquatur prius. Vide 2. Corinth. 3 [4ff]. Deinde novum dicitur propter novum populum; gentes puto, qui olim longinqui per sanguinem Christi propinqui facti sunt, et in testamento delegatum erat fore, ut benedicerentur gentes. Quae omnia Christus hoc loci etiam mortis suae fructum explicans fere sic ait, si modo paraphrasten tolleras: Hactenus imolate sunt in testamento veteri multae pecorum myriades, in quo Iudei solum habebantur pro populo dei; porro nunc istud tempus illuxit, quo prophetis satis fieri per me debet. Audistis ergo, quod corpus meum pro vobis expensurus sum, nunc quis inde fructus, haurite et accipite hoc vinum novi testamenti symbolon, hoc est eius rei, quod omnia per me innovata, completa, sacrificia antiquata et novus ille populus in testamentum intromissus sit per sanguinem meum, qui effunditur ad expiationem orbis, reconciliationem patris et populorum unitatem etc. - Nam sic interpretatur istaec Paulus ipse 1. Cor. 10 [1ff], Ephes. 2 [1ff]; quibus accedit etiam Christi verbum Luce 24 [47], ubi disserit de gentium vocatione et peccatorum remissa.

Verum tu simplicibus verbis domini credendum ais, cum tamen nos toti studeamus simplicitati, imo si istud est simpliciter ambulare, quaevis obvia et inexcussa arripere? Quid dices? Deum nemo unquam, sed Christum vidit orbis terrę; ergo non est deus! Ideo disscussione [!] opus in his et negociis similibus. In istis vero omnibus ubi vinum est sanguis? Audio sanguinem Christi semel effusum sufficere ad omnia omnium exhaurienda peccata, interim nihil de evocatione in pateras. Audio sanguinem Christi Iudęos pariter et gentes in unum cogere corpus, nulla interim de transmutatione mentio. Breviter: benedictio seu peccatorum remissa testamentum est, Christus testamenti mediator, mors vero et sanguis Christi testamenti reseratio et obsignatio, porro panis et vinum testamenti confirmati simbolon monens redemptionis et unionis. Vide cętera Ebrae. 9 [11ff]. Longiora dare non potui.

Debet ergo panis hic in fidelium coetu ita edi, ut institutus est 1. Cor. 11 [20ff]. Quare nihil nos movet, quod opponis, futurum, ut quivis panis significet corpus Christi. Tu videris, num ex singulari sequatur generale?. Apud sophystas quid consequatur, nescio; hoc autem scio, quod apud fideles omnia certo gerantur ordine 1. Cor. 14 [40]. Et cum addis denuo consequturum, ut in aliis sex milibus axiomatis «est» sumatur pro «significat», si hanc admiserimus propositionem: «Panis est corpus Christi» hoc est «panis significat» etc., experimentum fere dedisses te ignorare, qui loci quibus tropis ingressum praebeant. Verum irreverentia sacramenti in hunc fervorem te adigit. Sed dic sodes, an ne illi sacramento maiorem irrogent irreverentiam, qui ex eo nundinas adornant, an qui sanum eius usum produnt? Qui foedissimos inde ventres alunt, an qui pro gratiarum actione exponunt? Qui id pro deo ostentant ac pro carne mactant, an qui Christum ad dexteram sedere et sacrificium suum semel oblatum sufficere dicunt?

Vide nunc, vir bone, quis novum ritum inducat, et si non dedignaris, lege Oecolampadii libellum, in quo sensum horum verborum: «Hoc est corpus meum» reddit ex antiquis patribus. Certe ego non video, quomodo id novum dici debeat, quod tot scripturis tantisque nititur patribus. Faxit deus, ut mysterium suum sane ac pie intelligas. Ad hęc vero si respondere vis, fac, ut scripturis id fiat, ne cogar tibi obiicere, quod tu imerenti obtrudebas: pollicitum scripturas, quas tamen non reddiderim, cum tu interim nihil minus quam scripturas nostris opposueris.

Obtestamur autem per christianam charitatem, Christophyle dilectissime, ut Christum ardenter diligas, eius verbo adhęreas, illi gloriam et magnificentiam tribuas, hoc est, ut sis quod audis, Christophylum te non sine reverentia nominamus; tu adnitere, ut Christi studiosissimus sis, nostra vero boni consulas. Non deerit tibi Heimrychus ex animo tuus, modo in extremo saltem amicorum tuorum albo me subscribere dignaberis; id quod, mi Christophyle, efflictim efflagitamus. De Ioanne hic, quia alias tibi coniunctissimus, nihil scribo.

Interim peto, ut festinantis, imo inter magnas multasque negociorum turbas tumultuantis caracterem et dictionem Aristarchi obelo non confodias; nam quae scripsimus, ea celeritate scripsimus, ut postea relegentes, quod et ipsum vix semel contigit, ipsi multoties offenderemur.

Vive et vale in domino, Christophyle nobis charissime.

Ex Capell, trans Albim Tigurinorum coenobio, 3. calendas martias 1526.

Ioannes Enslinus et Heimrych Bullingerus, tui ex animo.</input>
  <output>Therefore, what is Christ calling new, if not uninterrupted? First, because all of the old type were fulfilled here and the truth itself is shown to us, which happened to them in figure. Thus, where there is new, the old precedes. See 2 Corinthians 3 [4ff]. Then it is called new because of the new people; I believe the Gentiles, who were once distant but were made close through the blood of Christ, and it was delegated in the covenant that the Gentiles were to be blessed. All these things, Christ, explaining the fruit of his death here, says almost thus, if you take away the paraphraser: So far, in the old covenant, many thousands of sheep have been sacrificed, in which only the Jews were held as God's people; but now this time has shone, wherein enough must be done for the prophets through me. Therefore, you have heard that I will spend my body for you; now, from whence comes the fruit, draw and accept this sign of the new covenant, that is the wine, which signifies that all have been renewed, fulfilled, the sacrifices made old, and that new people is introduced into the covenant through my blood, which is poured out for the expiation of the world, the reconciliation of the Father, and the unity of the people, etc. - For Paul himself interprets this in 1 Corinthians 10 [1ff], Ephesians 2 [1ff], to which Christ's word in Luke 24 [47], where he discourses on the calling of the Gentiles and the remission of sins, is added.

But do you say that we should believe the words of the Lord simply, when we strive for simplicity in all things, or if this is to walk simply, should we grasp anything that comes our way and is unexamined? What would you say? No one ever saw God, but the world saw Christ; therefore, he is not God! Therefore, we need to examine these and similar matters. In all these things, where is the wine the blood? I hear that the blood of Christ poured out once is enough to draw out all the sins of all, but there is no mention of calling them into glasses. I hear that the blood of Christ brings together Jews and Gentiles into one body, but there is no mention of transformation. Briefly: the blessing or remission of sins is the covenant, Christ is the mediator of the covenant, death and the blood of Christ is the revelation and confirmation of the covenant, and the bread and wine is the symbol of confirmation of redemption and union. See the rest in Hebrews 9 [11ff]. I could not give more.

Therefore, this bread should be eaten in the gathering of the faithful, as it was instituted in 1 Corinthians 11 [20ff]. Therefore, nothing moves us, which you offer, that it will be so that any bread signifies the body of Christ. You seem to be unaware, whether from a singular follows a general? What follows with sophists, I do not know; but this I know, that among the faithful all things are done in a certain order 1 Corinthians 14 [40]. And when you add again that it will follow that in the other six thousand axioms "is" should be taken for "signifies", if we admit the proposition: "This is my body" that is "this bread signifies" etc., you almost gave the experiment to not know the places where they give admission to tropes. But irreverence of the sacrament drives you to this fervor. But tell frankly, do they offer greater irreverence to the sacrament who adorn fairs from it, or those who proclaim the sound use of it? Those who feed the most disgusting bellies from it, or those who expose it for a thanksgiving? Those who show it for God and slaughter it for flesh, or those who say that Christ sits at the right hand and that his once-offered sacrifice is enough?

Now see, good man, who introduces a new rite, and if you do not disdain, read Oecolampadius' little book, in which he renders the sense of these words: "This is my body" from the ancient fathers. Surely I do not see how that should be called new, which so many scriptures and so many great fathers support. May God grant that you understand the mystery rightly and piously. But if you want to answer these things, do it with scriptures, lest I be forced to accuse you of what you impose on the ignorant: promised scriptures, which you nevertheless do not give, while you oppose nothing to ours but scriptures.

But we beseech through Christian charity, most beloved Christophyle, that you ardently love Christ, adhere to his word, give him glory and magnificence, that is, that you be what you hear; we name you Christophyle without irreverence; you strive to be most devoted to Christ, and you consult our good. Heimrych will not be lacking to you from the heart, only if you deign to subscribe me in the end at least to the list of your friends; which, my most beloved Christophyle, we most humbly beg. Of John here, since he was so closely connected to you, I write nothing.

Meanwhile, I ask that you not hack with an obelus the character and expression of the hastening Aristarchus; for we wrote with such speed that, when we reread, which hardly happened once, we ourselves often stumbled.

Live and fare well in the Lord, most beloved Christophyle.

From Capell, across the Rhine at the monastery of Zurich, February 29th, 1526.

John Enslinus and Heimrych Bullingerus, from the heart devoted to you.</output>
 </seg>

