
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Gnad und frid von gott dem vatter durch unßeren herren Jesum.

Alßo übel stath eß jezund in der wält, daß eß kein wunder ist, ob schon einer frommen tochter alleß daß argwönig, daß ihr auch guter meinung geschriben ist; daß mich zwaren dir hie zu schreiben gewent hete, wo du mich jezund etwaß jahren har nit der maß erkantist, daß mein hertz, gmüt und gedanck gar nit geneigt ist uff keinen list nach betrug frommer und einfalter mentschen, besonders zu dir, der mir in sonders erbar und lieb ist umb deiner zucht, einfalte und kintlicher geberden willen, welche mir also wenig ze muth sind zebetriegen oder einigeß wägs zu verletzen, daß ja mein höchster flyß sich alein (züg ich an minen gott himmels und der erden [Gen 24,3]) daruff ländt, daß din ehr und nutz an lib und seel geüffnet, ja gemehret werde. Der halben du jezund ane sorg und ohne allen argwon frei dißen brieff in stille läßen solt, mit fleiß und ernstlicher betrachtung, dan eß nit wenig an dem handel gelegen ist, den ich bring; so wirst du mir auch einen großen dienst mit dinem ernst bewißen, den ich aber zu alen zeiten umb dich zu beschulden geneigt bin.

Der allmächtig ewig gott hat unß von anfang geordnet in Christo Jesu zum ewigen leben, alßo daß wir in den fußstapffen dißers seines sohns heryn wandletind. Der selb aber hat unß ernstlich gelehrt, die wält und ihren fürsten mit sambt seinem rych der finsternuß flühen und die himmelischen ding annemmen, sitmal wir sterbliche mentschen gar ein kurtze zeit uff erden läbend und aber deß fleisches und der sünden lohn der ewig tod ist, deß geists aber und der tugent ewigs leben. Darumb je noht ist, daß wir alle, die in dem nammen gotes getauft sind und in in durch Jesum Christum zum ewigen leben vertrauwend, die wält und darin verlassend und unß gstaltind nach der bildtnuß gottes, nach welcher wir geschaffen sind [Gen 1,27; Eph 4,24; Kol 3,10] und die wir begehrend ewigklich zu niesßen [!]; welches aber dan beschicht, wen wir an uns nemmend ein tugentrych leben, welches, ob eß glich in vil ständen erfunden wirt, eß doch nirgent lebentlicher ußgetruckt dan in dem ehelichen stand, alß den gott selbs yngsezt hat und gebotten, daß alle die, so der hochen gaab der reinigkeit oder jungfrauwschafft nit fähig, vor allen dingen dißen stand annemmen sollend und ehe vatter und muter verlassen, wo sie ungeschickt, dan diße gottes ordnung underlasßen. So wir dan alle wüsßend, wie in großen ehren wir vater und muter haben sollend und wie gehorsam wir inen sein sollend, und aber gott alßo hoch die ehe achtet, daß er hie schlächt nit wil, daß auch die höchst gehorsamme kein hindernuß und uffzug in dißem stand gebäre, sehend wir heiter, wie hoch, thüwr und edel die ehe vor gott ist.

Darzu findend wir keinen stand in götlicher schrifft, der mehr verheißungen hab dan dißer, dan hie findend wir, daß der allmächtig gott verheißt, wie er sy beschirmmen wolle, leiten und erzühen in liebe, einigkeit und groser süße deß geists, in aller gerächtigkeit und in seinen gebotten; dan je in dißem stand sich alle tugenten üben könend: der glaub, liebe, barmmhertzigkeit, hoffnung, gedult, mäßigkeit, zucht und alle gottsäligkeit in Christo Jesu unßeren herren. Darumb wir auch sehend, daß die höchsten und alerthürwertisten fründ gottes [Jak 2,23] in keinem anderen dan disem stand gelebt habent, alß Adam, Enoch, Noe, Abraham, Isac, Jacob, Joseph, Moses, Aron, Josue, Gedeon, Samuel, David, Isajas und im newen testament Petrus, Paulus, Philippus, kurtz gar nach alle ußerwehlten gottes sammenthaft; auch uß den züchtigisten töchteren beider testamenten Sara, Rebecca, Lea Rachel, Ruth, Anna, Judith, Hester, Elisabetha und die muter unsers erlößers Jesu Christi, Maria, welche doch in der ehe alein ein einige ewige port und jungfrauw, wie von ihren Isajas [7,14] gewyßaget hat und Ezechiel, je daß wir hieruß gewüß erlehrnind, daß kein tugentricher, kein götlicher, kein früntlicher und lustbarer stand nit ist dan der ehelich. Dan waß ist also heilig und züchtig, waß ist also tugentrich und lieblich, daß dise gotes fründ [Jak 2,23] nit gewüst habent? Hetend sy ein beßeren und seel[igeren] stand gewüst vor got, so betend sie den selben angenommen. Sie habend aber in der ehe gelebt, so sol sich niemants uß den Christen merkhen lassen, sam eß nit seie ein lieblicher götlicher stand, ehelich syn.</input>
  <output>Grace and peace from God the Father, through our Lord Jesus.

Therefore it is so bad in the world nowadays that it is no wonder if one of the devout daughters be suspicious of everything that is written to her in goodwill; that I had intended to write to you here, who have not recognized me for some years now, that my heart, spirit and thoughts are not inclined to any deception of pious and simple people, especially to you, who is to me in special kind and dear for your modesty, simplicity and childlike behaviour, which are so little to my spirit to betray or to break any way, that my greatest effort alone (if I bring to my God of Heaven and Earth [Gen 24,3]) is that your honour and benefit be opened and increased in body and soul. Therefore you should now without any suspicion and without all suspicion leave this letter in peace, with diligence and serious consideration, as it lies much on the business I bring; so you will also show me a great service with your diligence, which I am however inclined to charge you with at all times.

The almighty everlasting God has from the beginning ordained us in Christ Jesus unto eternal life, so that we walk in the footsteps of this His Son. But He has earnestly taught us to flee the world and its princes with its darkness and to accept the heavenly things, since we mortal people live but a short time on earth and the reward of the flesh and of sin is eternal death, but the reward of the spirit and of virtue is eternal life. Therefore it is needful that we all, who are baptized in the name of God and trusting in Him through Jesus Christ unto eternal life, leave the world and fashion ourselves according to the image of God, according to which we were created [Gen 1,27; Eph 4,24; Col 3,10] and which we desire to enjoy eternally [!]; which however is accomplished if we take upon ourselves a virtuous life, which, though it is found in many states, is yet nowhere expressed livingly but in the married state, which God Himself has established and commanded, that all those who are not capable of the high gift of purity or virginity should in the first place take this state and not leave father and mother unless they are unable, then neglect this divine ordinance. So, knowing how highly we ought to honour father and mother and how obediently we ought to be to them, and that God holds the marriage in such high esteem that He does not here wish that the most obedient should bear any hindrance or impediment in this state, we cheerfully see how high, honourable and noble the marriage is before God.

Besides, we find no state in divine scripture that has more promises than this, for here we find that the almighty God promises how He will protect, guide and educate them in love, unity and great sweetness of spirit, in all justice and in His commandments; for in this state all virtues can be exercised: faith, love, mercy, hope, patience, temperance, chastity and all godliness in Christ Jesus our Lord. Therefore, seeing that the highest and most honourable friends of God [Jas 2,23] have lived in no other state than this, as Adam, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Joseph, Moses, Aaron, Joshua, Gideon, Samuel, David, Isaiah and in the new testament Peter, Paul, Philip, in short, all the elect of God together; also from the most chaste daughters of both testaments, Sarah, Rebecca, Leah, Rachel, Ruth, Anna, Judith, Esther, Elizabeth and the mother of our redeemer Jesus Christ, Mary, who yet in marriage alone was a unique and virgin, as her Isaiah [7,14] has surely foretold and Ezekiel, so that we learn from this certainly that no virtuous, no divine, no friendly and joyful state is there than the matrimonial. For what is so holy and chaste, what is so virtuous and delightful that these friends of God [Jas 2,23] did not know it? Had they known a better and more blessed state before God, they would have prayed for it to be accepted. But having lived in marriage, so no one of the Christians should show himself, unless it be a lovely divine state, matrimonial.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Dan zum ersten, so überwindt man all böß unglauben und ist man gfölgig gotes gebotten, die aber daß fleisch schwer bedunkend; so werdent zu gotes ehr die kinder erzogen und auch zu nuz der mentschen; so darf man frei zu got in nöthen lauffen und sprächen: Herr, ich hab dines wilens pflegen und dine bott gehalten, darumb so hilf, wie du wahrer gott verheißen hast! Und hie übt sich die hoffnung; gath eß dan wol, so ist danck dabei, alßo daß daß gemüth immerdar an gott haftet und er von gantzem hertzen geliebet wirt. Wan dan eins kranck, trurig oder frölich ist, hats dan alwegen einen einigen ewigen (der zeit) gespannen, der lieb und leid mit im tragt. Glich wie ein gild mit dem anderen mit halt, einß dem anderen dienstbar und behilflich ist, also ist auch hie ein unentliche liebe, bereite dienstbarkeit und unzertränliche einigkeit, daruff unser gott und schöpfer auch gespilt und geredt hat, «die zwei sollend sin ein lyb», je daß wo die ehe mit gott bezogen wirt, da ein unsagliche froüd auch im lyden selbs regiert und nimer biß zur prüfung gotes ußlöscht etc. Darvon alein denen, so solches erfahren habent oder in gottes wort und geist gelehrt sind zewüsßen ist, daß eß hie nit statt hat, mer darvon zu schryben.

Sprichst du: Wo sind frölich ehelüth, die also in gotsforcht lebend, in fröuden und ruw? Eß ist doch nüzit dan alle unruw, zanggen und schlagen etc. - Sich hie und merkh, daß der frommen lüthen nach vil sind und, ob got wil, täglich zunemmen werdint, so wir täglich gotes willen durch sein wort erlehrnend. Die wahren glaübigen sehend alein daruff, daß sie habind ein rein gewüssne und ein rüwig hertz, daß ist, daß sie mit got wol verricht seyent und ab im nit erschräkent, wen er kombt mit inen zu rächnen; daß ist daß höchste kleinot, daß wir uff erden haben mögend. Wo aber ein solich geruwet gemüt in got nit ist, da mag nüzid von ussen har kommen, daß solichen mentschen zu ruwen setze, und so dan etwaß unruwen und unraths in der wält im ehelichen stand, ist solches nit der ehe, sonder deren lüthen schuld, die solchen hochen stand nit rächt annemmend. Dan man ehen fint, die gar zwungen sind, so fint man, so alein umb deß guts wilen bezogen werdent oder aber uß holdschafft, daß ist uß unsinigkeit beschehend; danen har kombt, daß nach der trütel wuchen garkein frid ist. Wenig sind, die eß mit gott und der gerächtigkeit anhebend und weniger, die liebe, zucht und gotsforcht herin suchend. Waß kan aber da guts sein, da kein got ist? Und von danen kombt, daß sich die jungen göffel und oftmals auch die alten narren uff geerbts oder gewunen guts verlassend und nit hörend, 112 bis eß ales üpigklich verzeert ist. Da ist dan bulen, spilen, suffen, rasßlen, wullen, da heimben aber bei dem wyb murren, schelken, wüeten, schlachen, ja auch hunger, elend, armmuth und verachtung. So aber der mehrtheil in der ehe allein sein lust und nutz ohne got sucht, ist kein wunder, ob wir vil unlust in der ehe zu dißer zeit sächend, dan eß kurtz ab nit gsyn mag, daß da seie einigkeit, liebe und lust, da kein gotsforcht ist; sitmal rychthumb, wält, wolust ohne gott nüzid anders ist dan die hell hie und dort ewige verdammnuß. Eß ist ohne zweifel unsers unglaubens und unredlichen gmüts grächte straff von gott, dan die wil wir unßeren anfächtungen mehr nachgönd den gottes liecht und mehr sähend uf adel, rychthumb, pracht, stöltze, hoffart, wust, dan uf tugent, gotsforcht, deemut, treüw und zucht, beschicht unß grad rächt, daß wir dan also unfrüntlich dan [!] unvernünftig thier mit ein anderen lebend; wo man aber mit got die sach an die hand nimbt, übertrift zwaren gar kein stand dißen.</input>
  <output>First of all, by overcoming all evil disbelief and by being obedient to God's commands, which are sometimes difficult for the flesh, the children are raised up to God's glory and also for the benefit of humanity. Then one may freely run to God in need and say: "Lord, I have taken care of Your will and kept Your commandment, therefore help me, as You, true God, have promised!" Here hope is exercised; if it goes well, then thanks is due, so that the soul is always attached to God and is loved by Him from the heart. Whether one is sick, sad or happy, there is always one eternal bond that carries both love and sorrow. Just as one guild holds on to the other, one is of service and helpful to the other, so is there an infinite love here, ready service and indissoluble unity which our God and Creator has also spoken and declared, "the two shall be one flesh" so that joy in suffering itself is ruled by the unspeakable joy when married to God, and it never extinguishes until God's test etc. Only those who have experienced this or who are taught in God's word and spirit can be certain of this, that there is no point in writing more about it.

Do you say, "Where are the happy couples who live in fear of God in joy and peace?" It is useful then to all turmoil, discord and beating etc. - Look here and see that there are many pious people and, if it is God's will, they are increasing daily, so that we learn God's will daily through His word. The true believers look only to make sure that they are right with God and that they do not fear Him when He comes to reckon with them; that is the highest treasure we can have on earth. But where such a composed mind is not in God, something useful may come from outside to set such people at peace, and if there is any turmoil or disorder in the world in the married state, it is not the marriage itself, but the fault of those people who do not accept such a high state rightly. When marriages are found that are completely forced, one finds that they are only joined for the sake of property or out of greed, which comes from disagreement; then there is no peace after a little while. Few are those who take it up with God and justice, and even fewer who seek love, discipline and fear of God. But what good can there be where there is no God? And from this comes that the young people and often also the old fools rely on inherited or acquired property and do not listen until it is all squandered. There is then brawling, gambling, drinking, wrestling, quarreling, but at home the wife murmurs, scolds, rages, beats, even hunger, misery, poverty and contempt. But if the majority in marriage seek only their pleasure and benefit without God, it is no wonder that we find much unhappiness in marriage at this time, because it cannot be short that there is unity, love and joy where there is no fear of God; since wealth, world, pleasure without God is nothing else than the hell here and there eternal damnation. It is without doubt a punishment of our unbelief and dishonest mind that we seek our desires more than God's light and see more of nobility, wealth, splendor, pride, vanity, than of virtue, fear of God, humility, loyalty and discipline, which justly shows us that we thus live like unreasonable beasts with each other; but where one takes the matter in hand with God, no state surpasses this.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="3">
  <input>Alß ich aber solches und anders bei mir selbs gar nach bei 3 jahren ernstlich betrachtet hab und je allweg erfunden, daß ewiglich also bliben und frei mines libs sein weder von got nach der wält mir wol anstahn wil, daß ich keinen anderen weg zur tugent von sünden finden kan dan den einigen, den got verordnet, Christus Jesus anzeigt und dan mehrentheilß die fründe gotes gewandlet sind. Darzu mich auch mein ambt deß lehrens tringt, daß min lehr nit geistlich und leben üppig, auch vil ehrlicher lüthen und die mir zu gebieten hand rathend, hat mich noth bedunckt, daß ich mir hierzu einen eingen und ewigen (der zeit) gspannen ußerwehlte, mit dem ich disen stand rächter maaß annemme. Und wie wol mir darzwüschent etwas antragen, deß ich zwwaren [!] nit wirdig nach gnoß, hab ich doch nach nie (vilicht uß gotes ordnung) zu deren keiner min hertz und gmüt gesezt, dan du alein die einig bist, die ich mir fürgeschlagen. Got weists alein, ob du mir verordnet bist, und hat sich min wahl uff din red und geperden gegründet, alßo daß ich mir nach fürgebildet hab, du seyist ein solche, in deren gotsforcht und zucht seie und mit deren ich in lieb und leid und in allem, daß gotes wilen ist, leben möchte. Dennocht ligt solches zu einem theil an dir, zu mehrerem aber am gott. Dem selben sitmal ich wol vertrauwt, hab ich dißen brieff geschriben, auch dinen willen zu vernemmen, auch dinen stand zu hören, ob sichs also erfunde und gott unser schöpffer füegte, daß wir dißen früntlichen stand mit ein anderen bezugind. In dißem allem beschehe der wil gotes [Mt 6,10], die wil eß aber auch ein unglichß were, wan ich din willen und weßen erforderte von dir und du mineß nach nit bericht werist, so wil ich dir fürhin all min weßen fürhalten, guter hoffnung, wo du etwaß willen uß verordnung gotes zu mir hebist, thüeist glichß und flißist dich auch der warheit, die ich dir hie bei allen trewen schwere.

Erstlich mines wilens halb zu dir hast du jezund wol verstanden, daß, wo eß sich betreten möchte mit beider stenden, ich dir alein geneigt were; dan bilich ists, daß glichß zu glichem kum, und stath aber diße gliche nit im adel und richthumb, sonder zum höchsten in dem gmüt.

Demnach hat eß ein solche gstalt umb mich, und zum ersten ist dir ohne zweiffel von minem heimmat und minen elteren wol zu wüsßen, daß eß nüt weiters schribens bedarf; doch wurdist du nit uff di minnen, sonder uff mich sehen, mich wurdist nemmen und nit die minen, wie wol sie sind fromm biderb lüth.

So bin ich nie gewycht auch mit der minsten, wyche nit, bin frei, keineß herren libeigen, bin 23 jar alt, bin niemants uff erden nüzid schuldig und verbunden, wie die unfreien.

Ich hab auch von kints weßen uff mit gotes hilff also gelebt under den mentschen, daß ich an keinem ort nie einige unehr begangen hab, alßo daß ich nit dahin kommen bedörff, von danen ich gescheiden bin, ußgenommen wo daß evangelium Christi verhast ist daß aber dißen articel deß lümbdens nützid, antrift, dan Christus selbst geschmecht ist unbilich.

So hat got die gsundheit mines libs also vergaumbt und verhüt, daß ich innert 20 jahren nit alein kein nammhaft läger nie gehabt, sonder nie mit nambhafter kranckheit behaft geweßen bin, auch hüt zum tag (got seie min schirm!) keinen siechtagen underworffen bin, alß da sind blateren, hirn wüete, podagra, wasser sucht, fallen etc. Wol hab ich vom studieren ein blöd gsicht und zun zeiten ein blöd haubt, dahin auch hört, daß ich etwan gäch und zorn mütiger bin, doch nit häsßig und uffsezig, alß den wol nachlassen und bald vergäsßen kan, besonders wo man nit büchßen pulffer zu wirft.

Ich hab auch keinen anhang bößer buben, die mich ursachind zu spilen, daß ich doch nie lehrt, oder zu suffen und kriegen, ab dem ich ein grewel hab, oder zu bulen, welches ich zu vermiden der ehr nachstell; so hab ich kein kind niemants, der bei mir trag nach soüg, bin auch mit keiner der gstalt verhaft, daß mich gen dir leide etc. Ich hab auch sonst keinen anhang.

Auch so hab ich einen alten vatter ob den 60 jahren und ein muter ob den 55 jahren, auch einen bruder, ist 8 jahr elter dan ich. Dem selben und mir habend sie ales gemacht daß sie habend, trift jezund etwaß ungefährlich ob den 1400 lb, doch mit dißen gedingen, daß er sin leben lang herr darüber seie und ob er vor der muter mit tod abgienge, wir der muter keinen mangel ließind.

So hab ich sunst in unßerem closter min heimb wesen und einen guten stand; da bin ich uffgenommen alß iren einer vom convent, daß ich da lehre. Dahin oder wo ich je sin wurde, ich dich zu mir nemmen etc.</input>
  <output>When I had seriously considered this and other matters to myself for nearly three years and always found that to remain free from the ways of the world and to be truly pleasing to God was not possible without taking the single path which God has ordained, which Christ Jesus has revealed, and which the friends of God have followed, my duty of teaching also constrained me to take a particular and permanent companion who would accept this state with me. Although I was not worthy of any of those who were proposed to me, yet, perhaps by God's ordinance, I set my heart and mind to none other than you, who alone are the one I have chosen. May God alone know if you are ordained for me, and my choice is based on your words and promises. Therefore, I have taken you as an example, believing that you are one who is devout and obedient to God, and with whom I can live in love and sorrow in all that pleases God. Although much of this depends on you, most of it depends on God. Therefore, I have confidently written this letter to you and to hear your will and stand, if it should be found in God's ordinance and our Creator's pleasure that we enter into this friendly covenant. Let God's will [Matthew 6:10] be done, but it would be impossible if I asked your will and you did not report it to me; therefore, I will still keep all my will secret for the time being, in good hope that if you have something to say to me from God's ordinance, you will do it diligently and faithfully, and you will also swear to the truth that I have here solemnly promised you.

Firstly, so that you understand my will towards you, if it should happen that the two sides agree, I am inclined to you alone; for it is fitting that like should be joined to like, and especially in the mind, not in nobility or wealth.

Therefore, it is in this form around me, and first of all, you certainly know well from my homeland and my parents that there is no need to write anything else; but you should look at me and not my kin, take me and not them, however good they may be both in piety and people.

So I have never been a tenant, nor do I flee, I am free, not a servant of anyone on earth, I am 23 years old, I am not indebted to anybody on earth and obliged, like slaves.

From my childhood I have lived, with God's help, among men in such a way that I have not perpetrated any dishonourable act at any place I have been, so that I do not need to depart from where I have left, except where the gospel of Christ is hated; but this article of humility is profitable, for Christ Himself has tasted it as unbefitting.

God has so preserved the health of my life that I have not had any noteworthy illness in 20 years, nor have I ever been afflicted with any notable illness, and to this day (may God be my shield!) I have not been subject to any sickness, such as measles, brain fever, gout, dropsy, falling etc. True, I have gotten a dull sight from studying and sometimes a dull head, and I am sometimes too quick and hot-tempered, but I can easily leave it and soon forget it, especially when I do not throw books at it.

I also do not have any bad boys attached to me who would lead me to gambling, which I have not learned, or to drinking and quarrelling, which I hate, or to boasting, which I strive to avoid; I have no children of anyone under my care, and I am not bound by any means so that I would be hindered from coming to you, etc. I also have no other belonging.

I also have an old father of 60 years and a mother of 55 years, and a brother who is 8 years older than me. They and I have done everything they have, approximately 1400 pounds, but with this condition that he will be lord over it all his life and if he dies before the mother, they will not suffer any lack.

Otherwise, I have been living in our cloister and have a good position; I was taken there as one of their own, so that I could teach there. Whither or wherever I may be, I will take you with me, etc.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="4">
  <input>Die richthumb aber, die ich von den minen erben möchte, und der stand, den ich jezund hab, sind jezund gwüsß gnug, möchtend aber durch unfal (wie ale ding) werden geschwecheret. Darumb ich nach einen gewüßeren schatz hab, der gar nit fellen kan, der ist got; der hat mir auch kunst geben, welche, so ichs üben mit trewen, mir gewüßlich nützid geprästen wirt. Sunst seie eß von mir wit, daß ich die gaaben gottes verkauffen wolte; je ich weiß, daß mich gott nit verlast, die wil ich ihn für meinen gott hab. Dan sein prophet spricht: «Ich bin jung gsin und alt worden, hab doch nie den gerächten verla-sßen gesehen, nach sine kind umb brod gahn». Das schriben ich nur darumb, daß du nit vermeinist, ich wole dich züchen mit miner rychthumb. Wer uff richthumb und uff menschen all sein trost sezt, der ist verflucht [Jer 17,5] und hat keinen himmelischen gott in sinem hertzen. Merkh, bißhar hat man ale ding in clösteren, da der Endtchrist nach regiert, wolen gwüsß und gschliffen haben, nit wölen rächt uff gott vertrauwen; wo du dan auch hie woltist uff minen wolstand sehen und nit dabei auch erwarten, waß dir und mir got mit der zeit wurde zu liden geben, daß du dich dan frei an gott dörffist lassen, so wüsß, daß ich wenig herzens zu dir hete. «Dan wen got liebt, den sucht er» zun zeiten [Spr 3,12], und «alle, die gotselig wolind leben» - schribt Paulus -, «werdent verfolget».

[2 Tim 3,12]. Woltest den klagen und undultig sin, alein süßes bei mir suchen und nit daß sur auch versuchen, so wurde eß sich nit schickhen; eß sol ein lib sin, ein truren, ein froüd. Daß möchte ich mit dir, waß du mit mir, weist selbs wol und zum nützid, daß ich also frei schriben. Man muß ein ding heruß sagen, daß nit hernach ein unraht erwuchse. Ich wolte dir nüzid verwißen; daß wolte ich auch von dir haben. Eß darff nit vil hoffierens und zenzlens besonders hie, da man in daß lang jahr dinget, da kein scheiden hernach ist. Wan einer nur ein ful rosß kauft, besichtiget ers eigentlich, wie vil mehr hie, wen da kein enderung und wan der kauf einen schon gerüwt? Kurtz, wo gotsforcht ist und ein gmüt, daß mit got wol verrycht ist und dem nach daß sin wol kan zusammen halten und nit wulet, daß tragt lichtlich aleß, waß im got zu liden uffleit, und überkombt auch gnug ehren und guts, und daß mit gott. Wo daß nit, da werdent auch grose erb verthan mit schand und leid.

Darzu wüß auch, daß ich in keinen grosen gält schulden oder bürgschaften stäck, dan die ich samft wolte bezallen mit 3 gulden. So darff ich umb kleider in kurzem nit zu sorgen, sitenmal ich mine nit bald auch umb 50 gulden gebe. Sich, also gib ich dir trüwlich min weßen an in den mehreren stücken, damit du keinen betrug fürchtist.

Wüß auch, daß min ambt zu lehren (damit ich dir gar nüzid verhalte) lib und leben eingesezt hab, daß wo eß die noth, die warheit und got unßer herr forderte, ich den balg bei der warheit ließe. Von danen ich auch die morgen gaab nemmen, die ich dir geben wurde und glich mit dem patriarchen Abrahamb etc, dich got ze empfehlen und sprachen: «Got deß himmels und der erden» [Gen 24,3 u. ö.], got, der unß alen seel und lib geben hat, seie din schatz und din trost in Christo Jesu unßerem herren. Der verlasse dich nit, wie er mich auch nie verlassen hat, und erlüchte dich mit sinem geist, daß du in rächt kenist, an im ewig haftist und eß dultig 219 tragist, wo ich umb seines nammens willen den tod erliden müste etc.

Wo unß dan got auch kinder gebe und unß deß lebens gunte, woltend wir also huß haben, daß wir sy zu unsers gotes ehr und zu biderben lüthen erzugend. Wo wir aber darvon müstind, daß weiß ich, daß der herr unser got sie nit verließe, der doch alßo vil unnüzes spötliches gflügel gar wol erzücht, ja schadhafte thier wunderbarlich nehrt.

Aber waß darff eß vil worten? Suma sumarum, so ist diß der gröst gwüßist schatz, den du bi mir finden wirst: gotsforcht, frommkeit, trew, liebe, die ich uß der maßen wol an dich legen mag, arbeit, ernst, fleiß, daß unß in zitlichem nützid mangle. Alßo sichst hier vor augen ston, wan du mit mir da sur alß wol alß daß süß tragen woltist, wie du mich haben wurdist. Sunst sag ich dir nit von hochem adel und vil 1000 guldinen, zur nohturfft aber weiß ich wol, daß nützid wird gebrächen. Und spricht aber Paulus: «Nützid habend wir in die wält bracht, nüzid werdent wir auch hinuß tragen. Darumb wan wir kleider und spyß habend, ists gnug». Flüst dan auch rychthumb hinzu (alß got niemants nüzid abgeschlagen hat), ists ein ambt und schaffnerei.</input>
  <output>I understand that I have a good enough status and wealth that I have inherited from my family, but it could be weakened in the future due to misfortune (as with all things). Therefore, I have found a more certain treasure that cannot be lost, which is God; He has also given me skills which, if I practice them faithfully, will be of great use to me. Otherwise, it would be foolish of me to sell the gifts of God; I know that God will not abandon me, so I will keep Him as my God. As His prophet said: "I have been young and now I am old, yet I have never seen the righteous forsaken or their children begging for bread." I write this so that you do not think I am trying to win you over with my wealth. Whoever trusts in wealth and people instead of in God is cursed [Jeremiah 17:5] and does not have a heavenly God in their heart. Until now, it has been customary to have all things in monasteries, under the rule of the Lord Christ, to be certain and refined, not to trust in God; if you were to look at my wealth without also expecting what God will give you and me at the time, then you would know that I would have little heart for you. "For the Lord searches all hearts and understands every plan and thought" [Proverbs 3:12], and "all who live godly in Christ Jesus will be persecuted" [2 Timothy 3:12].

If you were to complain and be unaccommodating, only seek the sweet things from me and not try the sour, it would not be appropriate; it should be a mixture of joy and sadness, that I wish to have with you, as you know well and for our benefit, so that I may write so freely. One thing must be mentioned so that no harm arises afterwards. I wanted to be of use to you; I would also like to have that from you. It should not be much courting or flattery here, since we are dealing with something that is not to be parted with afterwards. If one buys a full horse, he inspects it thoroughly; how much more here, where there is no change and the purchase has already been agreed upon? In short, where there is fear of God and a spirit that is rightly with God and keeps together what God has commanded, that will easily bear all that God has commanded and will also receive enough honour and goods, and that with God. Where that is not, there will also be great inheritance with shame and suffering.

Furthermore, I know that I have no debts or obligations that I would have to pay with a large sum of money, except the three guilders that I would willingly pay. So I do not have to worry about clothes in the near future, since I will not be able to buy new ones for 50 guilders. Thus I give you my possessions faithfully in the larger pieces, so that you do not fear any deception.

I also know that my job to teach (so that I may be of use to you) has been established with life and limb, so that where it is necessary, the truth and our Lord God require it, I will leave the child with the truth. From which I will also receive the morning's gift that I will give you, and like the patriarch Abraham, etc., I will recommend you to God and say: "God of heaven and earth" [Genesis 24:3 and others], God who has given us all life and joy, be your treasure and your comfort in Christ Jesus our Lord. He will not forsake you, as He has never forsaken me, and He will illumine you with His Spirit, so that you may know rightly and cling to Him eternally and bear it patiently, even if I must suffer death for His sake, etc.

If God were to give us children and the gifts of life, we would have a house so that we could raise them to the honour of our God and to the benefit of people. But if we had to part from them, I know that the Lord our God would not abandon them, He who even so wonderfully nourishes so many useless and harmful creatures. 

But why many words? In short, this is the surest treasure you will find with me: fear of God, piety, faithfulness, love, which I can lay upon you in due measure, work, seriousness, diligence, so that we may lack nothing in temporal use. Thus you can see before your eyes, if you wanted to bear both the sweet and sour with me, as you would have me. Otherwise I do not speak of high nobility and many 1000 guilders, but for need I know well that use will be made. And Paul says: "We brought nothing into this world, and it is certain we can carry nothing out. Therefore, when we have food and clothing, let us be content" [1 Timothy 6:8]. But if one also adds wealth (since God has not denied anyone use), it is a job and service.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="5">
  <input>Alßo hast du bißhar min willen, min weßen und stand gehört, aleß mit der warheit, ohne faltsch dargethan. Jezund so heger ich auch an dich, wo dir etwas zu muth were, daß du mir auch dinen willen zu verstönd gäbist, gschriftlich oder wie eß dich je kommlich und gut dunkte; daß ist in summa, ob du möchtist in lieb und leid under miner trew und schirmm in der ordnung gotes leben, ob du ohne conscienz mögist din stand enderen, ob du ein hertz habist, huß zu haben und rahtsam zu sin, ob du guter gsundheit seyist und wie und waß diner muter und dinem bruder verbunden seyist. Je so bit ich dich, daß du mir ale ding alßo trüwlich anzeigist, wie du sichst, daß ich sy dir anzeigt hab. Besinn dich aber wol, daß du nüzid uß anfächtung thüeist, und sag eß frei heruß, schäm dich nützid, eß ist nüzid unehrlichs, so sagst auch niemand den mir. Nun hab ich doch dir vertrauwt und dir al min heimmlichkeiten geoffenbaret. Wüsß auch, daß ich dich in dinen worten nit fahen wil, bezüg ich mit dißem brieff. Biß frei, dan ich mich auch nit hiermit wil verredt haben, sitenmals ich mich mit dißem brieff alein hab wollen mit dir underreden; darumb die geschrifften, so zu verhüten allen betrug geschriben werdent, nit selbs betriegen oder erwütschen sollend. Demnach erst wolend wir die verpüntnuß und beschlusß antwort geben, wan wir beide hörend, waß willens und wie wir für ein anderen seyend. Du hast schon minen willen, so kanst uß obgemelten articlen verspüren, ob ich fur dich seie und warten alein deß dinen.

Hie weiß ich jezund auch wol, daß du dir hinder diser sach entsitzen wirst und vermeinen, du seyist ihren nit wyß gnug zu verantworten, darumb du vilicht uß forcht und schamm thun möchtist, daß dich hernach übel geruwe. Darumb so merk also wither. Zum ersten, so verstahst wol, waß ich dir schriben, daß ist die warheit, so weist demnach wol bei dir selbst zu einem theil, wie eß ein gstalt umb dich hat, zum anderen, waß du wol thun mögist; waß bedarf eß dan vil raths? Liß den brief 3 oder 4 mal, erinner dich dargegen, bit gott, daß er dir sin willen zu verstönd gebe. Nun ist doch nie-mants dir beßers schuldig dan du dir selbs; so wirstu mannen dir selbs, alein ist eß umb dich zethun. Da die lücht [!] ein anderen nit kenend und man die ständ nit weist, bedarf man vil rahts, hie aber hörst min stand und kenst mich. 2. Biß überhaubt nit so narrächt und unbsint, daß dir ützid jezund uß sorg fürnemmist. Ich kan wol bekenen, daß du jung bist, dir selbs entsitzst und dir vilicht in solchen sorgen fürbildist, du wolist nit uß dem closter und alweg also bliben, ohne man. Da hüt, daß warlich ein anfächtung were und die dich über kurtz übel gerewen möchte. Merkh alßo, du bist jung, so hat dir got nit alß ein ungschikten lib geben und dich geschaffen ohne zweifel nit, daß du ewig min gnedige frauw seyist und nützid thüeist oder kein frucht von dir komme.</input>
  <output>So you have heard my will, my manner and estate thus far, all with truth, without deceit. Now, I ask you, if you would like something in return, that you would give me your will, in writing or however it may seem fitting and good to you; in short, if you would like to live under my faith and protection in the order of God, if you can change your estate without conscience, if you have a heart fit for marriage and are sensible, if you are of good health, and how and what your mother and brother are bound to. Therefore, I ask you that you tell me all things truthfully, as I have told you. But take care that you do not act out of fear and say anything that you would later regret. For I have trusted you and revealed all my secrets to you. Know that I do not wish to trap you with my words, and I shall not be bound by this letter. Be free, for I do not wish to be bound by this letter, as I have wanted to converse with you alone; therefore, the writings that are written to avoid all deception shall not deceive or wrong. Therefore, first we shall give our agreement and conclusion when we have both heard what is willing and how we are to be for each other. You have already heard my will, so you can tell from the above articles if I am fit for you and await only yours. 

Now I know well that you will hesitate in this matter and fear that you are not wise enough to answer, perhaps out of fear and shame you would do something wrong that would later displease you. Therefore, take note. Firstly, understand well what I have written, for it is the truth; thus be wise in yourself in part, as to what form you should have. Secondly, what you can do well; what need is there for much advice? Read the letter three or four times, remind yourself of it, and pray to God that He will give you understanding. No one is more obligated to you than yourself; so you must take care of yourself alone. Since you do not know another and do not know the states, much advice is needed, but here you hear my state and know me. Secondly, do not be so foolish and hasty that you act out of fear. I can acknowledge that you are young, that you hesitate and perhaps act out of fear, that you would not leave the cloister and remain always thus, without a man. That would truly be a fear and something that could displease you shortly. Take note, you are young; thus God has not given you an unsuitable life and certainly has not created you to be my gracious wife forever and act out of fear or bear no fruit.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="6">
  <input>Lieber liß Paulum in 1. Epist. Tim. 2. cap. [9ff]; wirst finden, worin du must selig werden. Eß were ja ein narrächt fürnemmen (du habist dan die hoch gaab der reinigkeit ewiglich), wan du dinen jungen lib also woltist zwüschent den muren erstäcken. Hie biten ich dich, daß du dißer sach wolist eigentlich nachtrachten und jederman sagen laßist was er wol. Sich du uff gott, uff sin wort, worumb du seyist geschaffen, waß dines libs und diner seelen heil, auch daß du sterblich, nit lang uff erdtrich bist. Vergaum, vergaum, min liebe, daß du nit alweg im kumer hin lebist! Lieber sag an, kansts, worumb die frauwen clöster seiind anfenglich eingsezt. Nit daß man darin jung frauwen und töchteren, die aber anderst wo zu gut, erzuge, sonder die alten übelmögenden  armmen. Du bist im ze jung und zu wol mögend. Liß Paul 1. Tim. 5 [11ff], so verstand auch, waß dir hie fürgetragen werde. Wen ich schlächts glaub, daß also wenig für mich seve ein Greti dorffnepper, ein pürin, also wenig seie für dich ein rucher handtwerks man oder pur. So erforderen ich von dir auch nit hacken, rüten, sonder waß dir wol zimbt, huß zu haben, rathsam sin etc. und waß den wiberen ist. Wie wol in kurtzem vilicht nach nit vil huß habens bedörfte, die wil ich da were, möcht sich aber mit der zeit schicken, daß wir anderstwo hin kommind und nit me den tisch hetend, wie da, darvon wir wol reden wurdind etc. Hie bi gedenck auch, wie ein götlich lieblich ding eß ist, wo zwei eins mit ein anderen sind, einß dem anderen wol wil und sich eins deß anderen wol vermag, auch wie eß ein biter elend leben ist, wo zwei nit wol mit ein anderen zühend und wie nit jedes alzit sin fug fint etc. Daß alleß ich dir zu gutem schrib, daß dich wol vorbetrachtist und nit uß forcht oder schamm sagist, waß dir nit am hertzen seie, ja du wolist also bliben, und aber wüssentlichen anders in dir tragist. Wer weist, ob vilicht umb diner sorg, forcht und scham willen dir hie mit mir got ursach geben hat, dich frei ze eroffnen und zu freien, daß du je nit also müßist ohne frucht din junges leben in der gfengknuß verschlißen. Eß ist warlich ein groß ding, ursach haben und achten uff zit, daß wir jedes zu siner zeit, wan eß sich füegt, annemmind, wen nit alweg fürschleg sind, die unß fügind, und blibt aber zu lest grose reüw, wan wir die schantz habend übersehen. Diß ales jetzt stande zu dir hin, dan ich dir hiemit nit wil weder geliebet nach geleidet haben, sonder alein sag ich daß, daß du dich wol besinist, got, sein wort, diner seelen heil betrachtist. Waß dir dan got ingibt, daß thue; wirst mich in alweg unerzörnt haben, alein lasß mich ein antwort wüsßen.

Und so du jedoch gar keinß willen hetist, so biten ich dich doch durch die trew, durch die liebe und die ehr, die ich dir gun und zu dir hab, daß du mich doch in disem kleinen stuck verehrist und dißen brieff niemants sehen lasist, niemants nützid darvon sagist, sonder mir in widergebist und sechist, daß ich din ehr und nit schand gesucht hab. Ich hab dir stille schwigen, aler ehren und guts vertruwt, darumb hab ich gschriftlich wolen mit dir handlen, ich hab auch sunst keinem menschen uff erden nüzid darvon gesagt; müste auch fürder alßo bliben, biß zu siner zeit. Ich hete eß wol mögen muntlich verrichten, ich weiß aber, wo solichs, hete ichs nit könen. Die ander, die bi dir ist, were sie inen worden, wer sie nit auch darzu kommen, so weist selbs, daß sie dich danethin gehasset hete. Ich hab auch also dinen und minen verschonen wollen, habe keiner underthädinger gewölen; dinen, daß dir kein geschrei wurde, minen aber, so eß mir nit geriete, daß sich die nit froüwtend, die ich nit hab nemmen wolen. Darumb schon minen, dan ich auch dinen geschonet hab. Gedenck: «Waß über den anderen mund ußkombt, blibt nit verschwigen». Wan ich aber din wilen verstunde und wir möchtend eins werden, wolte ich demnach wol früntschafft erwerben an den dinen, so mit träffenlichen lüthen, daß sie nützid darwider kontind, doch ales mit dinem rath. Da schrib mir auch, wie eß umb din muter ein gstalt habe, du wirst mich alweg gutwilig finden. Ich meint, waß ich selbs bi dir nit schuff, wurde niemants anders schaffen. Ich vertrauw dir vil guts, darumb, were dir etwaß zu muth, so behalt disen brieff wol bi dir, daß du in bi dir behaltist, wan du zu mir komist. Antwort mir bald. In allem beschäch gottes wil [Mt 6,10]; der erlüchte dich, daß du daß annemmist, waß diner seelen heil seie etc.

Geben uff montag nach Michaeli im 1527. jahr.

Du känst min hand, daß mines nammes nit noth ist. Waß ich mit dir handlen, ist warheit ohne faltsch.

H. B.

Handel auch du wißlich in stille und schwigen, vertrauw mir, ich hab doch zum ersten dir vertrauwt. Got seie mit dir.

Mit eigner hand und sigel.</input>
  <output>Dear Paul, read 1. Epistle to Timothy 2:9ff; you will find what is necessary for you to become blessed. It would be foolishness to keep your young life hidden between walls. I urge you to consider this matter thoroughly and let everyone know what he needs to. Put your trust in God, in His Word, for why you were created, for the salvation of your life and soul, and that you are mortal and not long on this earth. Remember, remember, my love, that you don't live in misery all the time! Dear Paul, can you tell why women's cloisters were instituted in the first place? Not to raise young women and daughters who are otherwise well-off, but to care for the old, poor, and destitute. You are too young and well-off for that. Read 1 Timothy 5:11ff and understand what is being offered to you here. If I believe it would be little for me to be a Greti village rogue, a pauper, so it would be little for you to be a peddler or a poor. I do not ask you for hacking, rutting, but what suits you, to have a house, be wise, etc. and what is for women. As well, in the short term, you may not need to have a house, however, one may be necessary later when we go somewhere else and don't just eat at the table like we have been doing. Think of how it is a divine and lovely thing when two are with each other, wanting good for each other and comprehending each other, and how it is a bitter and miserable life when two are not in harmony with each other, and that everything is not always as it should be. I write all this to you for your consideration, so that you will not say out of fear or shame what is not in your heart, that you will stay this way, but knowingly carry something else in you. Who knows, maybe because of your worry, fear, and shame God has given you a cause here with me to open and free yourself, so that you won't have to lock your young life away without fruit. It is truly a great thing to have a cause and pay attention to the time, so that we take each in its time, if it is suitable, not always suggesting what suits us. There would be great regret in the end if we overlooked the treasure. All this now applies to you, for I do not want to neither love nor follow you, but only say that you should consider God, His Word, and the salvation of your soul. What God gives you, do it; you will have me always unoffended, just let me know a response.

And if you really do not have any desire, I still ask you through the truth, love, and respect I have for you, that you honor me in this small matter and that no one sees this letter, that no one tells anyone about it, but that you give it back to me and say that I have sought your honor and not shame. I have trusted you with silence, all respect, and goodness, so that is why I wanted to deal with you in writing; I have not told anyone else on earth about it; it must remain this way until its time. I would have liked to do it verbally, but I know where that would have led if I had not been able to. The others who are with you, if they had not come to it, you know that they would have hated you for it. I also wanted to spare you and me, not wanting to take any underlings; to spare you so there would be no outcry, but me in case it did not turn out well, so that those I did not want to take would not be glad. So I have spared both you and me. Remember: "What comes out of another's mouth does not remain secret." If I understood your will and we were to become one, I would gladly make friends with yours, so that they would not object, but all with your advice. Write to me also how it is about your mother, you will always find me well-intentioned. I think that if I had not done it with you, no one else would have done it. I trust you with much goodness, so if there is something to you, then keep this letter with you when you come to me. Answer me soon. In all things according to God's will [Mt 6:10]; may He enlighten you to take what is for your soul's salvation etc.

Given on Monday after Michaelmas in the year 1527.

You know my hand, so my name is not necessary. What I do with you is truth without falsehood.

H. B.

Also you handle wisely in silence and secrecy, trust me, I trusted you first. May God be with you.

With own hand and seal.</output>
 </seg>

