
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Jesus Christus, gottes und Mariae son verliche üch sinen göttlichen geist, daß ir inn alein erckennind das einig oberist guͦt sin damitt ir in einem guͦten glückseligen jar gantz selencklich läbind. Amen.</input>
  <output>Jesus Christ, God's and Mary's son, grant you His divine spirit, that you may recognize the one highest good alone, so that you may lead a very blessed and happy life in one good year. Amen.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Üwer letst warlich wyses, früntlichs und mir gantz anmuͤtig schryben hat mich, geliepten und dugentrychen wolgebor[en] frowen, uß der massen wol gefröuwt, und so vil me, so vil geneigter ich üch mir alle zyt befind. Ouch von üweren getrüwen bruͤderen hör, daß sy üch wol bedenckend und es üch uß der maassen wol gadt. Das kan mich warlich nitt gnuͤg und one end fröwen, besonders daß ir das kloster verlassen habend. Daran söllend ir gantz ghein rüwen haben, ist min ernstliche pitt, ja vil me gott dancken, daß er üch erlöst hat. Hie gedenckend jetzund der trostlichen worten Christi unsers heylands und siner apostlen. Christus spricht Mathaei 15 [9]: «Vergäbens eerend sy mich mitt menschen satzungen.» Nun ist das gwüß, daß üwer klosterläben und üwer orden ein menschen satzung ist. Dann Dominicus ist wol vor 400 jaren xin, und hat man darvor von Christus purt tusendt jar von keinem sölichen orden gewüst, ja üwer statt Bernn ist ettwas elter dann üwer orden. Dorumb üch nüt rüwen sol an dem stand, der so nüw ist von menschen angerycht, usset gottes wort, und in dem ir gott nüt gedienet hettind, lut siner worten. Imm Evangelio Luce am 17 [20f] spricht der herr abermols, das rych gottes stande nitt in usseren dingen. Also Paulus zuon Römeren am 14 [17]: das rych gottes sye «fryd, fröud und grechtigheit imm heyligen geist». So ists ye nitt kutten, orden, sibenzyt oder derley münchenthuͤmbs. Aber spricht er Ioan. am 8 [12]: «Ich bin das liecht der wellt. Wer mir volgen wirt nitt in der finsternuß wandlen.» Item der vatter züget vom himel Mathaei 17 [5]: «Das ist min lieber son, imm loosend»; und Paulus Colloss. 2 [3]: «In imm sind alle schetz der wysheyt»; und 1. Cor. 1 [30]: «Christus ist uns von gott zur wysheyt gäben»; item Mathaei 23 [10]: Christus ist unser einiger meister. So dem nun also ist und Christus die einig wysheit ist, das einig liecht, der recht meister, der die seeligheit alein gipt und weist worumb ers gibt, hette er doch billich der örden gedacht, wo sy not werend zum heyl. Er hat iren aber nienen gedacht, wie die heyligen gschrifft züget, die doch alles verfasset, das notwendig zum heyl ist: Ioan. 20 [31]; 2. Timo. 3 [14ff]. So ist ouch das klosterläben nitt not zum heyl, zuo dem daß es, wie obgemellt, dusent jar nach Christus purt erst uffgrycht ist. Dorumb habend ghein duren dran, fröwend üch üwer christenlichen fryheyt, und daß Paulus spricht 1. Cor. 3 [21]: «Alle ding sind üwer», verstadt ussere libliche ding, menschen uffsetz. Item 1. Cor 7 [23]: «Ir sind thür erckoufft, werdent nitt der menschen knecht.» Lieber läsend ouch das ander capittel zuͦn Collosseren [2,8ff] und das 4. cap. der Ersten epistel Pauli zuͦm Timotheo [1 Tim 4,1 ff]. Imm 5. cap. wil er schlechts nitt, daß man junge frowen in glübd uffnemme der reinigheit; sy söllind fromm sin, kinder zühen, huß hallten und nitt fuulen under einem valschen schyn deß geists. Läsend die ding eigentlich mitt urteyl, so erfindent ir, daß das warlich nitt ein gotsdienst ist, damitt man bishar umbgangen ist, sunder das, deß man wenig geachtet hat: glouben, liebe, unschuld, dugend, sorgsamme, hushaben, barmhertzigheyt, dultmuͤt, frid, kinder zühen, von sünden ston, das recht annemmen, lutergheyt, warheyt. Wie aber die ding in klösteren geballten, ist darby schyn, daß man die gantzen summ nun gebunden hat an götzenwerck, messen, schryen oder singen unverstandne ding, wachen, brummlen, spysen, kleider etc., alles ussere ding, deren doch die seel nitt besonderbars erfröwt ist, noch gott vereeret, dann es was nitt sin gebott, noch der nechst erbesseret, dann er sy mee engallt mitt ggeben und stüren etc., ye daß üch an dem verlassnen stand nützid duren sol. Sinnend vil me jetzund, wie ir jetzund wellend in gottes huld läben, all üweren trost, hertz, muͤt und sinn in dem einigen gott setzen, der alles erschaffen hat, der sinen son, unseren herren Jesum für unns ggeben hat, der ouch üch mitt seel und lib erschaffen hat; daß ir ja den selben alein anruͤffind, üch imm alein übergäbind und bittind mitt dem propheten David imm 5. Psal. [9]: «O gott, leyt mich in diner grechtigheit, mach mir dine wäg richtig und lycht». Flissend üch, daß ir niemands beleidigind, daß ir yederman, so vil an üch stadt, guͤts thuͤgind, das die armen üwer geniessind, daß ir üweren lib dem geist underthuͤgind und üwerem herren Jesu nachvolgind in demuͤt, guͤte, liebe, gedullt, verzyhung, reinigheyt, zucht und erbergheyt: so wirt alle hochfart, zorn, haß, uffsatz raach und was unrecht ist, niergend by üch bliben. Habend ir die hoch gaab von gott, so blibend also gott stiff und stät mitt hertzlichem anbauten: 1. Corinth. 7 [7f]; habend ir sy nitt, so thuͤnd das üch aber gott mitt sampt sinen apostlen heist Mathaei 19 [4ff], 1. Corinth. 7 [1ff], 9 [5], 1. Timoth. 3 [1ff], 4 [3ff], 5 [9ff], Titum 2 [4], Hebraeos 13 [4]. So ir dann also in gotsforcht läbind, so werdint ir gott vil baß gefallenn, dann hettind ir trissig wyler uff! Nemend min trost und instruction imm besten an, dann ichs uß getruwem früntlichem gmuͤt gethon hab.</input>
  <output>Your most wise, friendly and very humble letter has greatly rejoiced me, dear and noble lady, and the more I am the more I am inclined to you at all times. I also heard from your trustworthy brothers that they think of you very well and it pleases them greatly. This truly rejoices me without end, particularly that you have left the cloister. You should have no regret for this at all, it is my earnest request, rather you should give thanks to God that He has liberated you. Now thinking of the comforting words of our Saviour and His apostles. Christ says in Matthew 15 [9]: “Vainly they worship me with the precepts of men.” Now it is certain that your cloister life and your order are a human precept. For Dominic has only been for 400 years, and before Christ there was no such order known for a thousand years, and your city Bern is even older than your order. Hence you should not regret the state which is so new from human effort, apart from God’s Word, and in which you have not served God according to His words. In the Gospel of Luke at 17 [20f] the Lord again says that the kingdom of God stands not in outward things. Also Paul said to the Romans at 14 [17]: the kingdom of God is “peace, joy, and righteousness in the Holy Spirit”. So it is not habits, orders, sevenfold vows or the like monkery. But He says in John 8 [12]: “I am the light of the world. He who follows me shall not walk in darkness.” Again the Father calls from Heaven in Matthew 17 [5]: “This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased”; and Paul in Colossians 2 [3]: “In Him are all the treasures of wisdom”; and 1 Corinthians 1 [30]: “Christ is given to us from God for wisdom”; also Matthew 23 [10]: Christ is our one and only master. So since it is thus and Christ is the one wisdom, the one light, the right master, Who gives and shows bliss alone and why He gives it, He should certainly have thought of orders where they were needed for salvation. But He thought nothing of them, as the holy Scriptures testify, which yet set forth everything required for salvation: John 20 [31]; 2 Timothy 3 [14ff]. Therefore cloister life is not necessary for salvation, seeing that, as mentioned above, it was only set up a thousand years after Christ. Hence you should have no regret for leaving the state which is so new from human effort, apart from God’s Word, and in which you have not served God according to His words. Think rather now how you should now live in God’s grace, setting all your comfort, heart, spirit and mind in the one God, Who has created all things, Who has given His Son, our Lord Jesus, for us, Who has also created you with soul and body; that you may call upon Him alone, give yourselves up to Him alone and pray with the Prophet David in Psalm 5 [9]: “O God, lead me in Thy righteousness, make Thy way plain and light before me”. Take care that you offend no one, that you do good to everyone as far as lies in your power, that the poor may partake of your goods, that you subject your body to the Spirit, and follow your Lord Jesus in humility, goodness, love, patience, forbearance, purity, discipline and modesty: so that all pride, anger, hatred, revenge and whatever is wrong shall nowhere remain with you. If you have the great gift from God, stay thus steadfast and constant in due devotion to God: 1 Corinthians 7 [7f]; if you have not, do it yet by God with His apostles as He commands in Matthew 19 [4ff], 1 Corinthians 7 [1ff], 9 [5], 1 Timothy 3 [1ff], 4 [3ff], 5 [9ff], Titus 2 [4], Hebrews 13 [4]. If you then live in God-fearing manner, you shall highly please God, since you have thirtyfold! Take my comfort and instruction to heart, for I have done it out of a true and friendly spirit.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="3">
  <input>Hie antwurtend jetzund selbs, was ir thuͤn wellind; ob ir das Wygerhuß kouffen und ein Bernner werden wellind. Lügend und verantwurtends wyslich.

Deß mechtigen uuszugs halb und erlicher lüten ins feld verordnet sind wir ouch sust berycht worden, aber nitt so häll alls ir das gethon. Loben den allmechtigen gott, daß er die sinen nitt verlaast. Gloub ouch, er werde ein eerliche, hochverruͤmpte statt Bernn fürhin erbauten (wo sy by imm bstond, alls ich nitt zwyfflen) wie bishar, und sy mitt grossen eeren und guͤt begaaben etc. Ich schicken üch hie ein lied, ist der statt Bernn ze lieb gemachet von dem handel von einem Zurycher, und bitten, ir wellind mir umb das helfen, das Venner Walter hiervon gemachet hat.

Es ist ouch mir üwers bruͦders faal von hertzen leyd. Imm und üch allen widerfaart, das der prophet Salomon in Sprüchen am 3. cap. [12] spricht: «Wen gott liebet, den heimsuͤcht er zuͤn zyten». So ist ouch sellten fröud one leyd; beschicht von gott, daß wir sinen nitt vergessind etc. Iren gruͤtz ist mir träffenlich angnäm, embüten inen ouch hiemitt minen willigen dienst, minen früntlichen gruͤtz und was ich inen liebs, eer und guͦts vermöchte. Also ist ouch min pitt, ir wellind mir frow Catherinen, üwere schwester früntlichen gruͤtzen etc.

Ich dancken ouch üwer muͤy und arbeyt, besonders günstige frow, daß ir üch so vil habend bemuͤyen mögen und mir biß in die langen nacht schryben. Kan wol verston, das ir vil mögend umb minet willen dulden, ouch mitt sömlichem ein rechten gunst zuo mir tragend; derhalben ir mich allwägen alls ein guͤten fründt finden werdent, also ouch, daß ich mich nitt bald mitt gunst, liebe und guͤthet wirt überwinden" lassen" etc.

Das ir mir schrybind, der radt üch von mir ggeben sye trostlich und eerlich, fröwt mich nitt ein wenig, dann ich üch gern das radten wellte, das üwer nutz, fug und eer. Wyters schrybens halben wundert mich alein; dann thuͤnd ir wie ich, so schlahend ir vil an in abwäsen, die üch doch in bywäsen vor fröüd und vile der hendlen nitt mee zuo sinn kummend, zuo dem, das die gschrifft wolbedacht, yffrig und wys ist. Daß ir ouch sprächind, ir wellend imm nachsinnen, thuͤnd ir wyslich, dann man spricht: «Wol besinnen verhont nie ghein sach.» Aber zum ersten thuon, und darnach radt suͦchen oder besinnen ist ein dorheyt. Dorumb Salustius [!] sprach: «Ein yedes ding soll mitt ryffem radt vorbetrachtet werden und, so es dann erraten, sol es unverzogen dappfferlich zehand genommen werden.» Besähend ouch die welt nun wol; sy last sy anesähen und doch nitt schnell erduren. Alle wellt ist vallsches voll, dorumb thuͤnd ir imm recht und zum wysisten, daß ir üch imm end in gottes willen ergäbend. Dann wer in gott vertruwt, wirt nitt ze schanden, spricht sin heyliger prophet Isaias [49, 23].

Zum letsten ist min trungenliche früntliche pitt, ir wellend min schryben guoter meinung empfahen, dann, so es zuo dem üweren gelegt, ist es gar kleinfüg. Gedenckend, daß man spricht, die lüt, so glich nitt wol reden könnind, syend gar nitt ze betriegen geschickt, sunder die früntlichosten, alls die vil hefftiger imm hertzen und der thaat syend dann die wort lutend.

Hiemitt dancken ich üch aller eeren und alles guͦts, embüt mich das ze widergellten, wie ich könde und mir müglich. Gott sye mitt üch.</input>
  <output>Now answer for yourself what you would do; whether you would buy the Wigern house and become a Bernner. Act wisely and responsibly.

Because of this mighty journey and the honest people sent into the field, we have also been reported of this, but not as much as you have done. Praise the almighty God that he has not abandoned his own. I also believe that he will build an honest, highly respected city of Bern (where they are in his protection, as I do not doubt) as before, and fill it with great honor and good gifts, etc. I send you here a song, made in honor of the city of Bern by a merchant from Zurich, and I ask you to help me with the version that friend Walter has made of it.

It is also a great sorrow to me from the heart of my brother. May God and you all have a good journey, as the prophet Solomon says in Proverbs 3: [12]: "Whom God loves, he chastises in due time". So there is seldom joy without sorrow; trust in God that we do not forget him, etc. Your greeting is very pleasant to me, I also return my willing service, my friendly greeting, and whatever of love, honor and good I could do for you. Therefore, my prayer is that you will send friendly greetings to my friend Catherine, your sister.

I also thank you for your diligence and hard work, especially the gracious lady, that you have taken so much trouble for my sake and written to me until late at night. I can understand that you have suffered much on my behalf and have been friendly towards me; therefore you will always find me as a good friend, and also that I will never be overcome by kindness, love and goodness.

That you write to me the advice given to you is comforting and honest, it does not trouble me at all, for I would like to advise you what is useful, profitable and honorable. As for further writing, I only wonder; for if you do as I do, you will suffer much in your absence, which in your presence would not cause so much of the handling, since the writing is well thought out, enthusiastic and wise. That you also say that you will consider it, you act wisely, for one says: "Well consider never fails in any matter". But to do first and then seek advice or consider is a wisdom. Therefore, Sallust [!] said: "Everything must be considered with due care and, when it is guessed, it must be taken up immediately with diligence." Consider the world well; let her look and not endure quickly. All the world is full of falsehoods; therefore do what is right and wisest, that you surrender yourselves to God's will. For whoever trusts in God will not be ashamed, says his holy prophet Isaiah [49, 23].

Finally, my humble friendly prayer is that you will receive my writing favorably, for as it is laid before you, it is quite humble. Remembering that one says, those who cannot speak well are not at all capable of deceit, but the friendliest are more in the heart and in the deed than in the words.

With this I thank you for all honors and all goods, and I regret that I cannot repay you as I can and as is possible. God be with you.</output>
 </seg>

