
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Wie ich üw[er] ersam[en] wysh[eit] vor vergangner tagen ein zyl 14 tagen zugemutet hab darinn ich ü[wer] w[ysheit] ein entliche antwurt gäben möge, hat sich darzwüschend ein ersammer radt miner h[erren] von Z[ürich] erckant: sidmal ich inen mitt eydspflicht, von Cappel har langend, verbunden, söhe ich still ston und niemands nützid zuͦ sagen biß uff wyterenn bescheyd. Darzwüschend habend mich beyde rät einhällencklich zuo iro prädicanten erwellt ann deß abgestorbnen M[eister] H[uldrych] Z[wingli] seligen statt. Welchs ich ü[wer] w[ysheit] himitt [!] kundtthuͤn, damit ir nitt wyter verzyhind, und sag üch ouch, ersamme und wyse herren, minen höchsten danck; üwer trüw und liebe, so ir zuo mir gehept will dero den tag und ich lieb [!] zu gutem nimmer vergässen. Und bitten üch hieby zum höchsten, gnädigen herrenn, ir wellind üch zöugernn disers brieffs an min statt lassen befolhen sin; dann er ze Bremgarten lütpriester gewäsen, sich eerlich und gepurlich getragen hat, ist ouch der maß berycht und gelart inn dem handel gottes, daß ir in allwäg mitt imm versorget werind.

Hiemitt etc.</input>
  <output>As I have humbly requested of your wisdom on a certain day 14 days ago, that I may give a final answer to your wisdom, an honorable council of my lords of Zurich has recognized it in the meantime. Therefore, I am bound to them by oath from Cappel, to remain silent and not to be of any use until further notice. In the meantime, both councils have unanimously elected me as their preacher in the place of the late Master Huldrych Zwingli, blessed be his memory. I hereby inform your wisdom of this, so that you may not be further delayed, and give my highest thanks to you, honorable and wise lords, for your loyalty and love which you have shown me; I will never forget that day and will love it well. And I humbly beseech you, gracious lords, to allow this letter to be followed in my stead; for he who was a priest at Bremgarten, who conducted himself honorably and faithfully, is also reported and praised in the service of God, that you may always be provided with him.

Herewith etc.</output>
 </seg>

