
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Dem ersamen frommen Marxen Rosen sye «gnad und frid von gott dem vatter und unserem heiland Jesu Christo» [Tit 1,4].

Nach dem und du dich by uns erlich, redlich und christenlich hast gehalten, besunders in trüw und dienstbargheit gegen jedem und allen, allermeist aber gen mir, hab ich nitt mögen lassen dan ich schribe dir ettwas, daruss du besserung und nutz empfahen möchtest, also das din dienst gen mir nitt umbelhonet blibend.

«Uffs erst dancke ich gott durch Jesum Christum» [Röm 1,8], das er dich zum teil uss siner gnad und grundlosen barmherzigheit in erckantnuss hat ingefuͤrt sines göttlichen worts, also das din nichtigheit von Adam angeboren erckenst und dorumb alein Christum suͤchst, «welchen uns gott hatt fürgestelt zum gnaden stuol» [Röm 3,25], fürsprecher, versönung, erlöser, grechtigheit, hieland [!] und wysheit. «Denn es ist das wollgefallen gottes gesin, das in imm allein alle völle whonen sölt und alles durch inn versönet wurde zuo imm selbs, es sy uff erden oder in hymel, darmitt» - wie Paulus spricht -, «das er frid macht durch das bluͦt an sinem krütz durch sich selbs» [Kol 1, 19f].

Und warlichen so sind wir uss uns «von natur nüt anders dan kinder des zorns» [Eph 2,3], daruss aber gottes unergrüntliche barmherzigheit erglastet: «Dan wir nu uss genad selig werdend durch den glouben, und dasselb nitt uss uns, es ist gottes gab, nitt us den werchen, uff das sich neimandt [!] rüme» [Eph 2, 8f]. Die werch sind aber wir schuldig zuo thuon, ja die uns gott durch den glouben und schrifft leert, nitt selbs erdichte werch, die dan nie wol Sauli erschussend: 1. Reg. 15. [1 Sam 15,1 ff]. Solomon spricht darvon Proverb. 3: «Vertrüw dem herren uss gantzem dinem hertzen und verlass dich nitt uff din fürsichtigheit. In allen dinen wegen halt inn im hertzen, und er wirts wol machen» [Spr 3,5f]. Sich, das sind christenliche werch: alle ding imm glouben thuon, alles imm übergeben und inn lassen walten, darbin [!] ander lieben und anderen thuon was wir wöltend, das man uns thet [Mt 7,12]; Roma. 12 [9ff] und 13 [8ff]; ouch 1. Ioan. 3 [11ff]. «Gebenedyet sy ouch gott und der vatter Jesu Christi» [2 Kor 1,3], der dich also erlüchtet hat, daß du erckennen kanst, wie alle ding gott in allen würckt [1 Kor 12,6]. Wan als der prophet spricht, so ist sinen der tag, sinen ist die nacht [Ps 74,16] und er verwandlet zyt und die alter; und Paulus: «Es ist ein herr, ein gott und vatter unser aller, der da ist über uns all und durch uns allen und in uns allen» [Eph 4,5f]. Welches, so es kundt gesin ist dem fromen Hiob, kont er gar wol gedult haben; dan er wust, das sin kranckgheit und armuot von gott was. Ouch David, do er sprach: «Ist es gefellig dem herrenn, so komb ich wider in min rych. Ist es aber sach, daß er spricht: du gefalst mir nüt, so bin ich bereit» [2 Sam 15,25f]. Also leer, min lieber bruͦder Marx, gott, dinem herren dancken und alles heimstellen, gott, dinem vatter wol vertrüwen in allen sachen und in hertzlich bitten. Des du aber, gott sye gelopt, ein guoten anhab hast gegen mir erzuͤgt in dem du din handel alein gott dem herren zuoschript. Du sichst je jetzundan schimbarlich und häll, wie dich gott on din ratschlag, thuon und verdienen in er und guot gesetzt hat. Welchs er dorumb gethon hat, das du imm lartest vertrüwen und des imm zuo dancken. Wann also hat er je und je die kinder von Israhel durch guothet zuo imm gezogen. Dorumb soltu dich nu fin in handel schicken, gott vor ougen haben und im vertrüwen, wan er ouch nitt alein den lib und die eer, sunder ouch alles guot gibt.

Es stat geschriben Ioan. am 10 [28], das die schäfflin Christi Christo niemandt wirt uss der hand rouben; deshalben er sich ouch ein hyrten nemmet [Joh 10,11]. Daruss nu klar ist, das wir gott dem herren die seel vertrüwen muͤssend, und nu dem also ist, wer wolt dan nitt den lib können oder wellen gott übergeben? Den er sich aber erbüt, wie er sölle von imm erhalten werden, wann wir je gottes wort habend durch den propheten usgesprochen Psal. 36. [Ps 37,3-5. 7.25]: «Hoff uff den herren und thuo guͤts, blib im land und mere dich im glouben. Hab din lust am herren, der wirt dir geben, was din hertz lust. Befil dem herren dine weg und hoff uff inn, er wirts wol machen. Halt dem herren still und lass inn mitt dir machen. Ich bin je jung gewesen und alt worden, und hab noch nie gesechen den grechten erlassen oder sinen samen umb brot gan».</input>
  <output>I humbly pray to God the Father and our Saviour Jesus Christ [Tit 1,4] for mercy and peace. Since you have faithfully, honestly and Christianly kept yourself with us, especially in loyalty and service to everyone and everyone, but especially to me, I could not help but write something to you, from which you might receive improvement and benefit, so that your service to me will not remain unrewarded.

"First of all, I thank God through Jesus Christ" [Rom 1,8], that He has, out of His grace and boundless mercy, brought you to the knowledge of His divine word, so that your nothingness, inherited from Adam, may be recognized and therefore only seek Christ, "whom God has appointed for us as a seat of grace" [Rom 3,25], intercessor, reconciliation, redeemer, righteousness, saviour and wisdom. "For it is pleasing to God's will that all fullness should dwell in Him alone and be reconciled to Himself, whether on earth or in heaven," - as Paul says - "that He might make peace through the blood of His cross by Himself" [Col 1, 19f].

And truly, we are "by nature nothing else but children of wrath" [Eph 2,3], from which, however, God's unsearchable mercy is gladdened: "For we are saved by grace through faith, and this is not of ourselves; it is the gift of God, not of works, lest anyone should boast" [Eph 2, 8f]. But works we are obliged to do, yes, those which God teaches us through faith and Scripture, not self-invented works, which would never please Saul, 1 Sam. 15 [1 Sam 15,1 ff]. Solomon speaks thereof Proverb. 3: "Trust in the Lord with all your heart and do not rely on your own understanding. In all your ways acknowledge Him, and He will direct your paths" [Prov 3,5f]. These are Christian works: to do all things in faith, to give everything to Him and to let Him rule, to love others and to do to others what we would want done to us [Mt 7,12]; Rom. 12 [9ff] and 13 [8ff]; also 1 Ioan. 3 [11ff]. "Blessed be also God and the Father of Jesus Christ" [2 Cor 1,3], who has enlightened you so that you can recognize how God works in all things [1 Cor 12,6]. When, as the prophet says, the day is His, the night is His [Ps 74,16] and He changes the times and the ages; and Paul: "There is one Lord, one God and Father of all, who is above us all and through us all and in us all" [Eph 4,5f]. Which, if it were known, would have been endured by the pious Job, for he knew that his sickness and poverty were from God. Also David, when he said: "If it pleases the Lord, I will return to my kingdom. But if He says: you do not please me, I am ready" [2 Sam 15,25f]. So learn, my dear brother Marx, to thank God, your Lord, and to restore everything to God, your Father, to trust Him in all things and to pray to Him with heartfelt prayers. But you, to God's praise, have already shown a good attitude towards me in that you ascribe all your dealings only to God, the Lord. You can see now that God, without your advice, has done and deserved you in good and kind. That He has done this, that you might trust Him and thank Him for it. For thus He has always drawn the children of Israel to Him through goodness. Therefore, submit yourself now to the dealings, have God before your eyes and trust Him, for He not only gives life and honor, but also all good things.

It is written in John 10 [28], that the sheep of Christ will not be robbed out of His hand; therefore He also takes for Himself a shepherd [John 10,11]. From this it is now clear that we must trust the soul to God, the Lord, and now that is so, who would not be able to or want to give life to God? But He offers Himself, how he should be received from Him, when we have God's Word spoken by the Prophet Psal. 36. [Ps 37,3-5. 7.25]: "Trust in the Lord and do good, stay in the land and strengthen your faith. Delight yourself in the Lord; He will give you the desires of your heart. Commit your way to the Lord and trust in Him; He will bring it to pass. Be still before the Lord and wait patiently for Him; I have been young and now am old, yet I have never seen the righteous forsaken or his seed begging for bread".</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Sich, lieber bruoder, das sind die wort gottes; mögend gar nüt felen. Hastu nu glouben in sine obgemelte wort, wol dir und du solt gott teglichen bitten, daß er gnad mitt dir thuͤye, das du inen mögest glouben. Nitt minder ists, die versuochung kumpt, und also hert, daß du meinst, du muͤssest verderben, verharr du aber stiff im glouben. Wann wen du glöubig bist, «mach sich gott selber nitt lougnen» [2 Tim 2,13]; er muͤs halten was er hat zuo gesagt. Wir lesend, das er versuocht hat den frommen Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, und Hiob. Abrahae liess er nemen sin schöne husfrowen Saram, beruͤfft in uss sinem vatter land, gab im nütisterminder nitt eines fuͤsbreits zuo besitzung [Apg 7,5]. Hiob nam gott lib und guot. Nu sy aber standhaft blibend im glouben, wurdendt sy okt verlassen und kamend zuo grosser rychtumb. Also soltu nach dem gebott gottes werchen ernstlich, den es geschriben stat: «Im schweis dines angsichts wirst essen dines brot» [Gen 3,19], und lass gott walten. Lass im die sorg und nun du an dich das werck oder die arbeit und lis im Evang. Mathei das 6. und Luce 12. cap. [Mt 6,25ff; Lk 12,22ff]. Lass dir ouch Jacob, den heiligen ertz vatter nitt uss dinem hertz kummen, welcher, ob er wol in Mesopotamia, Syrie nitt einer hand breit hatt, ward er doch rych uss gott und siner arbeit: Genes. 29 [1 ff; 30,25 ff].

So hab ich gesprochen, das du eer und guͤt habist überckummen und das dorumb geschriben stat Gene. 1 und 2: «Und gott gesegnet sy und sprach zuo inen: Sind fruchtbar und merend üch und füllend die erden» etc. [Gen 1,28]. «Der man wirt vatter und muͤtter verlassen und sinem wib anhangen, und werdendt sin zwei ein fleisch» [Gen 2,24]. Daruss du mercken solt, wie du den eelichen stand verbringen und wie du din wib halten söllest, also dast in eer und gout [!] blibest.

Am ersten wirt der eelich stand recht verbracht, wann man kinder zuͦ eeren gottes darvon zücht, von welchem nu nitt stat ist zuo reden, so man sust wol wüst, was zuo der eelichen pflicht höret. Das du aber allwegen das wort gottes vor dir habest, so nim für dich und lys das 7. cap. der ersten zuͦn Cor. Wie man aber muͤsse und sölle die kind uffzüchen, hast im letsten buͤch Mose: Deutro. 7 [6,20ff].

Zum anderen solt din wib halten wie din eigen fleisch. Dorumb Paulus spricht: «Ir man, liebend üwere wyb, glych wie ouch Christus geliebet hat die gmeind und hat sich selbs für sy geben, uff das er sy helgete» etc. [Eph 5,25f]. «Also söllend ouch die menner iren wyber lieben als ir eignen lib. Wer sin lib liebet, der liebet sich selbs. Den jemandt hat nie sin eigen fleisch gehasset, sunder ernerets und pflegt sin, glich wie ouch der herr die gmeind» etc., Ephe. 5 [28 f]. Also spricht ouch Petrus: «Ir menner, whonend by inen mitt vernufft und gebt dem wybischen als dem schwechsten werchzüg sine eer, als ouch mitterben der gnad des lebens, uff daß üwere gebet nitt verhinderet werdent» [1 Petr 3,7]. Sichstu nu, daß es nitt muͤs mitt bochen, kriegen, schlahen zuogan, und des heb dich verwegen; wo zangg ist und hader, do ist ouch ghein guots. Das aber vil sprechend: ich wil die min meisteren mitt knütlen sind narren und wüssend nienerumb nüts; söltend stockfisch für wyber haben, dan die selbigen sind vil knütles nötig.

Siche, das ist nu die meinung gottes, dorumb er dich in den eelichen stand beruͤfft hat, ja daß du inn vor ougen habist, imm vertrüwist, in suochist, im danckist, lieblich, früntlich und christenlich by dinem wyb whonist, kinder zühist etc. Sich, min bruoder und geliebter gottes, heist das nüt: in eer und guot gesetzt? O, danck im nacht und tag, wann du imm nitt gnuͤgsamlich dancken magst! Eere sye imm alein! Ja, sprich ich abermals, du solt die gegeben gnad nitt verschupfen, sunder in dem willen gottes leben. Dorumb wirt dir nu hie am aller notwendigosten werden, das du sin ewig göttlich wort nitt verlässest, sunder, so dir gott die gnad thon hatt, das du lesen kanst, ein Testament kouffest, daruss man den willen gottes erckennet, und das selbig imm hus mit den dinen zuo siner zyt uͤbist. Magst wol besehen, was ungmach denen volget, so das wort nitt annemend, und was glücks denen vorstends ist, die sich des worts haltend: Levitici 26 [3 ff], Deutro. 28 [1ff]. Es stat geschriben: «Verfluͤcht sye, wer nitt alle wort disers gsetzts uffrichtet, das er darnach thuͤye. Und alles volck soll sagen: Amen». Deutero. 27 [26].

Hüt, das din ee nitt brechest; wan grösserer diebstal uff erd nitt ist, sittundmal du dinem eichen gmahel iren eigen fleisch entwendst, das dan grosse sünd vor gott ist und je und je herten glich gestrafft an lib und seel, ouch (wie wol es jetzund, leider, gott erbarmbs, gering geachtet wirt) mitt dem schwert gericht. Es stat geschriben: «Verfluͤcht sye, der da beschlafft die husfrowen sines nechsten. Und alles volck soll sagen: Amen». Deutro. 27, [20.22].</input>
  <output>Dear brother, these are the words of God; may nothing fail. If you now believe in His aforementioned words, it will be well for you and you should daily ask God that He may grant you grace that you may believe in them. It is no less true that temptation comes and so hard that you think you must perish, yet if you remain steadfast in faith. When you are faithful, "God will not deny Himself" [2 Tim 2:13]; He must keep what He has said. We read that He tempted the righteous Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and Job. He let Abraham take his beautiful wife Sarah from her father's land, giving him not even an inch of possession [Acts 7:5]. God took away Job's wealth and possessions. Yet they remained steadfast in faith and although they were forsaken, they came to great wealth. So you should diligently do according to the commandment of God, which is written: "In the sweat of your face you shall eat your bread" [Gen 3:19], and let God rule. Let Him take care and you take the work or the task and read the Gospel according to Matthew 6 and Luke 12 [Mt 6:25ff; Lk 12:22ff]. Do not let Jacob, the holy patriarch, depart from your heart, for although he had not even a hand's breadth in Mesopotamia, Syria, he yet became wealthy through God and his work: Genesis 29 [1 ff; 30:25 ff].

So I have spoken that you may have honor and good overcomes and what is written in Genesis 1 and 2: "And God blessed them and said to them: Be fruitful and multiply and fill the earth" etc. [Gen 1:28]. "The man shall leave his father and mother and cling to his wife, and the two shall become one flesh" [Gen 2:24]. From this you should know how you should conduct the marital state and how you should treat your wife, so that you remain in honor and good [!].

First, the marital state is rightly conducted when children are raised to the honor of God, of which it is not necessary to speak, if one knows what belongs to the marital duty. That you, however, always have the word of God before you, take this for yourself and read the 7th chapter of the first to the Corinthians. How, however, the children must and should be raised, you have in the last book of Moses: Deuteronomy 7 [6:20ff].

Secondly, you should treat your wife as your own flesh. Therefore Paul says: "Husbands, love your wives, just as Christ also loved the church and gave Himself for it, that He might sanctify it" etc. [Eph 5:25f]. "In the same way, the husbands should love their wives as their own bodies. He who loves his own flesh loves himself. For no one ever hated his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, just as the Lord also does the church" etc., Ephesians 5 [28f]. So also Peter says: "You husbands, dwell with them according to knowledge and give honor to the female as the weaker vessel, and as also joint heirs of the grace of life, that your prayers not be hindered" [1 Pet 3:7]. Do you see now that it is not necessary to go with books, wars, beating, and do not be bold; where there is discord and strife, there is no good. That many say: I want my masters to be fools with knuckles and know nothing; they should have stockfish for wives, then these are much knuckles needed.

Behold, this is now the opinion of God, why He has called you into the marital state, yes that you have it before your eyes, trust in it, seek it, thank it, live lovingly, friendly and Christianly with your wife, raise children, etc. Behold, my brother and beloved of God, is not that called: to be set in honor and good? O, thank Him night and day, when you can not thank him enough! Glory be to Him alone! Yes, I say again, you should not reject the given grace, but live in the will of God. Therefore it will now be most necessary to you that you do not leave His eternal divine word, but, if God has granted you the grace that you can read, buy a Testament, from which one recognizes the will of God, and that you practice the same in your house with your own at his time. You can well see what misfortune follows those who do not accept the word, and what luck stands to those who keep the word: Leviticus 26 [3 ff], Deuteronomy 28 [1ff]. It is written: "Cursed be he who does not keep all the words of this law to do them. And all the people shall say: Amen". Deuteronomy 27 [26].

Beware, do not break your oath; for greater theft on earth is not, than when you take away your spouse's own flesh - that is a great sin before God and ever and ever severely punished in body and soul, also (however it is now, alas, God have mercy, little regarded) with the sword. It is written: "Cursed be he who sleeps with the wife of his neighbor. And all the people shall say: Amen". Deuteronomy 27, [20.22].</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="3">
  <input>Du solt niemandt zuo vil abnemmen, sunder alein din lidlon empfahen, wann ghein unrechtes gout truͤyen mag und ist ein haller mitt friden der gwüssne in gott besser den ghein schiff nobel jemer werde. Was ists, ob es glich ander thünd? Soltu dorumb sömliches ouch thuon? Schlechlich [!] ist obgemeltes innemmen ein gottlosse thuss, wan alle die, so das vollbringend, sind verzwifflet an gott, wellend in fürkumen und rych werden, es sye gott lieb oder leid. Sy sehend darzuo, es stat geschriben: «Du solt nitt zweierlei gwicht in dinem sack, kleines und grosses, haben; und in dinem huss soll nitt zweierley mes, gross und cklein [!], sin. Du solt ein völlig und recht mes haben, uff das din leben lang were uff dem land, das dir der herr, din gott, geben wirt. Den wer sölchs thuot, ist gott, dinem herren, ein grewel, wie alle, die übels thuond». Deutero. 25 [13-16].

Frömbd herren und usslendig krieg soltu vor allen dingen wie tödtlich gifft miden; wann was jomer und grossen hertzen leids, gottlose und kranckheit drus entspringe, sehend wir leider in unseren eilenden verblenten kriegstropfen. Es stat geschriben: «Verfluͤcht sye, wer geschenckt nimpt, das er die seel des unschuldigen bluots schlecht. Und alles volck soll sagen: Amen». Deutro. 27 [25].

Du solt dich ouch in gheinem weg partyen. Lass disen luterisch und ehenen zuinglisch sin, und bis du ein christ. Lass jederman machen; du muͦst ouch alle ding nitt verantworten. Bis schidlich und red allwegen zuo allen sachen das best. Bis früntlich gegen jederman, wann dir wol ze wüssen ist, wie din gwerb stat. Uss den gassen und win kempffen entstat selten guots, 1. Timoth. 6 [3 ff].

Vermid unzytlichs fressen und suffen, zuo trincken, schlaff trünck. Gelust dich aber nei was das duo bi dinem wyb und bi den dinen. Im monat gang enist zum win; daß dir huld machest und behaltest, setz dich zur erbergheit und zuo den dinen. Bis wacker, züchtig, frölich und underdienstig. Es stat geschriben: «Suffend üch nitt voll wins, doruss ein unordlich wesen volgt» etc, Ephes. 5 [18]. Spilen und böse gsellschafft soltu wie din verderpnus flühen, schwerren und kostliche kleidung miden, unzüchtige wort nienan in din mund nemmen. Wan hie nitt gnuͦgsam mag usgesprochen werden, wie bös schedlich ding spilen ist und böse gsellschafft, ouch wie es so verlumbdet machet. So soll unsere red ja ja sin und nein nein [Mt 5,37]. So bedarf es ouch gheiner syden nitt; wann wir bedeckt sind, ists gnuog. «Nüt bringend wir in die welt» [1 Tim 6,7], «nackend muͤssend wir hinuss» [Hi 1,21]. Heb das din zuo samen und heb huss, wie eim frommen man zuo stat. Es stat geschriben: «Huorery aber und alle unreinigheit soll nitt under üch genempt werden» etc, besich Ephes. 5 [3].

Und daß ich min schriben nu fürhin ende, so thuo als eim christen zuo stat; halt dich des göttlichen worts, welchs dich rychlich in allen dingen grecht fuͤrren kan, und fuͤr ein erbars, christenlichs, gotsförchtigs leben, also das du nach disem leben ewige ruow besitzest. Amen. Nun dis min kurze instruction zum besten an, wann sy in grosser ummuos [!] ilends geschriben ist. Grütz mir hernn schultheis Ruͤplin, Sigmunden, Mörickovernn, den praedicanten und ander bruͤder in Christo, und «die gnad gottes sy mitt dir» [1 Tim 6,21].

Von Kappel, des 5. tags hornung 1525.

Heimrych Bullinger, din williger diener.

Psalm 127 [Ps 128]:

«Vol dem, der den herren fürchtet und uff sinen wegen gadt! Du wirst dich neeren diner henden arbeit; wol dir, du hasts guot! Din wib wirt sin wie ein fruchtbar winstock an den wenden in dinem huse, dine kinder wie die öl zwy umb dinen tysch her. Sich, also wirt gesegnet der man, der den herren fürchtet. Der herr wirt dich segnen uss Syon, das du sehest das glück Hierusalem din leben lang und sehest diner kinder kinder. Fryd über Israel!»</input>
  <output>Do not take too much from anyone, but only receive your portion, for no wrongful good can be brought and one who is content with peace is better than one who is noble but without peace. What does it matter if it is different? Should you therefore do the same? It is said that taking such things is an ungodly deed, for all those who do it are doomed by God, wishing to become wealthy and rich, whether God wills it or not. Behold, it is written: "You shall not have in your bag two kinds of weights, a large and a small. Nor shall you have in your house two kinds of measures, a large and a small. You shall have a perfect and just measure, that your days may be long in the land which the Lord your God is giving you. For whoever does these things, those who deal dishonestly, are an abomination to the Lord your God" (Deut 25:13-16).

Above all, you should avoid foreign lords and foreign wars, like a deadly poison; for what sorrow and great grief arises from godless and sickly wars, we sadly observe in our hasty and blind warring. It is written: "Cursed is he who accepts a bribe to slay an innocent person. And all the people shall say: Amen" (Deut 27:25).

You should also in no way be a partisan. Let this be Lutheran and that Zwinglian, and be a Christian. Let everyone do as they will; you must not be responsible for all things. Be prudent and always speak the best when it comes to all things. Be friendly to everyone, when it is well known to you how your profession stands. From the streets and taverns seldom any good arises, 1 Tim 6:3ff.

Avoid excess eating and drinking, excessive sleeping and revelry. But be modest with your wife and with those who are yours. Go to the tavern once a month; so you may earn and keep honour, set yourself up as an example and for those who are yours. Be brave, disciplined, cheerful and obedient. It is written: "Do not be drunk with wine, in which is dissipation; but be filled with the Spirit" etc (Eph 5:18). Avoid playing and bad company, like you would avoid your own destruction, shun expensive and luxurious clothing, and do not utter indecent words with your mouth. For here it cannot sufficiently be said how bad and shameful playing and bad company is, and how it debauches. So let our speech be yea yea and nay nay (Mt 5:37). So it needs no further explanation; for we are covered, that is enough. "We brought nothing into this world" (1 Tim 6:7), "naked we shall depart" (Job 1:21). Gather this together and keep house as is fitting for a pious man. It is written: "Let no filthiness nor foolish talk be named among you" etc (Eph 5:3).

And since I now end my writing, do as is fitting for a Christian; hold fast to the divine word, which can richly direct you in all things and lead you to a holy, Christian and God-fearing life, so that you may possess eternal rest after this life. Amen. Now this is my brief instruction for the best, however it is written in great haste. Greet for me Herrn Schultheis Rüplin, Sigmund, Mörickover, the preacher and other brothers in Christ, and "may the grace of God be with you" (1 Tim 6:21).

From Kappel, the 5th of February 1525.

Heinrich Bullinger, your willing servant.

Psalm 127 [Ps 128]:

"Blessed is every one that feareth the Lord; that walketh in his ways. For thou shalt eat the labour of thine hands: happy shalt thou be, and it shall be well with thee. Thy wife shall be as a fruitful vine by the sides of thine house: thy children like olive plants round about thy table. Behold, that thus shall be blessed the man that feareth the Lord. The Lord shall bless thee out of Zion: and thou shalt see the good of Jerusalem all the days of thy life. Yea, thou shalt see thy children's children, and peace upon Israel"</output>
 </seg>

