
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Edlen, vestenn, ersammen, frommen, fürsichtigen, wysen, gnedige und lieben herren, min willig dienst und was ich üch ze guͤten und gefallen wüste bevor.

Erstlich sagen ich gott danck durch Jesum Christum [Röm 1,8], das er üwer ersamm wyßheyt in sinem wort behallten hatt, und bitten inn von hertzen, er welle üch fürohin sterckenn.

Demnach das üwer wyßheyt mir kleinfuͤgem, unnwirdigem und unverdientem so demuͤtig und trostlich zuͦschrybend, minen ouch zuͦ üwerem predicanten begärend, sag ich ü[wer] w[yßheyt] hohen danck, will ouch üwer eeren trüw und liebe ind eewigheyt nitt vergässenn, sunder mitt allem vermügenn, wo ich möchte und könde, mitt trüw, ghorsamme und bestem flyß beschulden. Wellt ouch, das es gott also gefuͤgt hätte, das ich üch, minen gnedigen herren vonn Bernn hätte dienen mögen, zuo denen ich alle zyt, allß zuͦ wysen, gotsförchtigen und getrüwen, ein besonderbar hertz getragen hab. Dann hett es ouch nitt gheines bittens bedörffen, und noch nitt, wo ich ü[wer] w[yßheyt] willfaren möchte.

Nun aber hatt es gott also gefuͤgt, daß mich mine herren vonn Zürych angenommen habend, denen ich vonn ettwas jaren har mitt eydspflicht, allß ich ouch M. Frantzen ze Bremgarten eigentlich vorgemeldet hab, verbunden bin. So habend sy ouch iro predicanten alle zyl dem göttlichen wort uffgenommen und fry befolhenn ze predgenn, luth der gschrifft h[errn] Berchtolden zuͦgeschickt. Dorumb bitt ich, üwer ersamm wyßheyt welle nützid an mich zürnen, dann ich eerenhalb nitt hab anders handlenn mögen. Wellind mich ouch nützid minder üch befolhenn haben; dann hatt es glich jetzund die gestallt, will ich doch allwäg ein Berner und der üwer sin mitt gunst und trüwen diensten, wo ich kan.

Deß botten halb, hat er nützid versumpt, sunder ylends und getrüwlich gesternn zwüschend 7 und 8 morgens die brieff überantwurt.

Damitt sye ü[wer] w[yßheyt] gott befolhen, der welle üch in eeren, fryden und wolstand lang behallten.

Datum Zürych, 14. decembris anno 1531.

Ü[wer] w[yßheyt] underthäniger

Heinrych Bullinger.

Den edlen, vesten, frommen, fursichtigen und wysen herren schuldheyssenn und radt der statt Bernn, minen gnädigen unnd liebenn herrenn.</input>
  <output>Greetings, honorable, wise, pious, prudent, wise, gracious and beloved lords, my willing service and whatever I might know to be good and pleasing to you. 

First of all, I give thanks to God through Jesus Christ [Rom 1,8], that he has kept your wisdom in his word, and I earnestly ask him to strengthen you from now on. 

Therefore, since your wisdom has written to me, an insignificant and undeserving one, so humbly and comfortably, also asking for my service to you as a preacher, I give you my highest thanks, and I will not forget your honor and love in eternity, but rather with all my strength, as much as I can and can, I will show loyalty, obedience and the best effort. If you also had it God's will that I could serve you, my gracious lords of Bern, I have always had a special heart for the wise, god-fearing and loyal. It would not have needed any request, nor does it now where I could wish your wisdom well. 

Now, however, God has so arranged it that my lords of Zurich have taken me in, to whom I have been bound by an oath of loyalty for some years, as I have also reported to M. Frantzen in Bremgarten in person. So they have also taken all their preachers to preach the divine word according to the writings of the Lord Berchtolden. For this reason, I ask your wisdom to be merciful to me, since I could not act otherwise on your behalf. They have also shown me mercy by not requiring me to follow them; it has the same arrangement now, yet I am always a Bernese and one of yours with favor and loyalty, as much as I can. 

For the messenger's sake, he has not neglected, but rather faithfully yesterday between 7 and 8 in the morning, delivered the letter. 

May God bless your wisdom, that he may keep you in honor, peace and prosperity for a long time. 

Dated Zurich, 14th of December, 1531. 

Your wisdom's humble 

Heinrich Bullinger.</output>
 </seg>

