
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Mein williger dienst myns kleynen vermoegens altzeit zofoern.

Lieber Heinriche, dusser myn guder frunt plegt bin uch zo handelen.Lieber Heinriche, dusser myn guder frunt plegt bin uch zo handelen.So hait er offt von myr gehoirt, wie ich eynen guten frundt daeselbs habe.Lieber Heinriche, dusser myn guder frunt plegt bin uch zo handelen.So hait er offt von myr gehoirt, wie ich eynen guten frundt daeselbs habe.Hait myr darum zogereedt, habe ich etwas hinuff zo schrieben, er wills gern mit im foeren.

Wie woll ich sunders neit zo schrijben weys dan van unser aller (dem herren sy lob) gesuntheit.Wie woll ich sunders neit zo schrijben weys dan van unser aller (dem herren sy lob) gesuntheit.Was sunst leufficher hendell by uns weren, als mit rustung widder den Turcken, wirt er beß muntlich vertzellen.Wie woll ich sunders neit zo schrijben weys dan van unser aller (dem herren sy lob) gesuntheit.Was sunst leufficher hendell by uns weren, als mit rustung widder den Turcken, wirt er beß muntlich vertzellen.Moigt ir im gude anwysung syner hendel thoin, beger ich synent wegen.

Wyder ist myn bitt, das tu na fridden, so vill durch gott moegelich, arbeitz, und laiß mich verstain, ab uch myn letste brieb behandicht.

UrAnnotaciones in canonicam epistolam Ioannis schickt myr doch tzo, dan ich habe die lest gesanten eynem Augustiner monnich in fruntschaff geleint, kan si nitt widder krygen, und was ir sunst gefertigt.UrAnnotaciones in canonicam epistolam Ioannis schickt myr doch tzo, dan ich habe die lest gesanten eynem Augustiner monnich in fruntschaff geleint, kan si nitt widder krygen, und was ir sunst gefertigt.Und enbuet myr dairgegen, was du gern von myr hettes.UrAnnotaciones in canonicam epistolam Ioannis schickt myr doch tzo, dan ich habe die lest gesanten eynem Augustiner monnich in fruntschaff geleint, kan si nitt widder krygen, und was ir sunst gefertigt.Und enbuet myr dairgegen, was du gern von myr hettes.Will mich in glychen und merrem altzeit vlyssigen.

Groitz myr all gute frunde.

Adolfus [Bitter], myn neye, hait zo Wittenberg und Bruyswick studiert, ist neulich by uns gesyn und widder gereist.Adolfus [Bitter], myn neye, hait zo Wittenberg und Bruyswick studiert, ist neulich by uns gesyn und widder gereist.Laist dich seyr groitzen und spricht, das Martinus, Ph[ilippus], Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius und etliche mehr anderen hefftig widder uch kempffen [in] yren sermonen des sacramentz halber.Adolfus [Bitter], myn neye, hait zo Wittenberg und Bruyswick studiert, ist neulich by uns gesyn und widder gereist.Laist dich seyr groitzen und spricht, das Martinus, Ph[ilippus], Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius und etliche mehr anderen hefftig widder uch kempffen [in] yren sermonen des sacramentz halber.Moigt ir myr kortz verfaste schrifft und scharffe zostellen.Adolfus [Bitter], myn neye, hait zo Wittenberg und Bruyswick studiert, ist neulich by uns gesyn und widder gereist.Laist dich seyr groitzen und spricht, das Martinus, Ph[ilippus], Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius und etliche mehr anderen hefftig widder uch kempffen [in] yren sermonen des sacramentz halber.Moigt ir myr kortz verfaste schrifft und scharffe zostellen.Will verschaffen, das sy Martino ach Ph[ilipp]o uberantvort werden, mit anhangender bitt, daruff zo antworden.Adolfus [Bitter], myn neye, hait zo Wittenberg und Bruyswick studiert, ist neulich by uns gesyn und widder gereist.Laist dich seyr groitzen und spricht, das Martinus, Ph[ilippus], Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius und etliche mehr anderen hefftig widder uch kempffen [in] yren sermonen des sacramentz halber.Moigt ir myr kortz verfaste schrifft und scharffe zostellen.Will verschaffen, das sy Martino ach Ph[ilipp]o uberantvort werden, mit anhangender bitt, daruff zo antworden.Will dich mitt dussen kortzen dem almechtigen befollen haben.Adolfus [Bitter], myn neye, hait zo Wittenberg und Bruyswick studiert, ist neulich by uns gesyn und widder gereist.Laist dich seyr groitzen und spricht, das Martinus, Ph[ilippus], Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius und etliche mehr anderen hefftig widder uch kempffen [in] yren sermonen des sacramentz halber.Moigt ir myr kortz verfaste schrifft und scharffe zostellen.Will verschaffen, das sy Martino ach Ph[ilipp]o uberantvort werden, mit anhangender bitt, daruff zo antworden.Will dich mitt dussen kortzen dem almechtigen befollen haben.Laist mich doch verstain von uren handelen, anslegen und fridden der Eydgnossen.

Datum zo Coln, 12. augusti anno 32.

Dirich [!] Bitter van Wipperfoird, scholmeister zo Sant Ursulen.

Dem ersamen und waillgeliertenn Maister Heinrichen Bullinger, meinem gunstigen frundt zo handenn.Dem ersamen und waillgeliertenn Maister Heinrichen Bullinger, meinem gunstigen frundt zo handenn.Gen Zuͤrich.</input>
  <output>My willing service of my small means is always available to you.

Dear Heinrich, this my good friend often tells me how I have a good friend in himself. Dear Heinrich, this my good friend often tells me how I have a good friend in himself.Therefore, he often asked me to write something to him, and he would be happy to take it with him.

As to what I would write without fail, I would tell of the health of all, to the praise of the Lord. As to what I would write without fail, I would tell of the health of all, to the praise of the Lord.What more pleasing enterprise could there be among us than to take up arms against the Turks, which he will tell you more about verbally. As to what I would write without fail, I would tell of the health of all, to the praise of the Lord.What more pleasing enterprise could there be among us than to take up arms against the Turks, which he will tell you more about verbally.May you give him good advice about his dealings, and I beg you on his behalf.

Furthermore, my request is that you work for peace as much as possible with God's help, and let me know how you treated my last letter.

Send me the annotations on John's canonical letter, for I lent the last one to a Augustinian monk in friendship, and I cannot get it back, and whatever else you have prepared.Send me the annotations on John's canonical letter, for I lent the last one to a Augustinian monk in friendship, and I cannot get it back, and whatever else you have prepared.And offer something to me in return for what you would like from me.Send me the annotations on John's canonical letter, for I lent the last one to a Augustinian monk in friendship, and I cannot get it back, and whatever else you have prepared.And offer something to me in return for what you would like from me.I will always be willing and more in the same.

Greet all good friends for me.

Adolf [Bitter], my nephew, has studied at Wittenberg and Brunswick recently, he was seen by us and has now gone again.Adolf [Bitter], my nephew, has studied at Wittenberg and Brunswick recently, he was seen by us and has now gone again.He is greatly esteemed and says that Martin, Philipp, Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius and many more have been strongly opposed to you in their sermons about the Sacrament.Adolf [Bitter], my nephew, has studied at Wittenberg and Brunswick recently, he was seen by us and has now gone again.He is greatly esteemed and says that Martin, Philipp, Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius and many more have been strongly opposed to you in their sermons about the Sacrament.May you send me a short, firm letter and sharp reply.Adolf [Bitter], my nephew, has studied at Wittenberg and Brunswick recently, he was seen by us and has now gone again.He is greatly esteemed and says that Martin, Philipp, Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius and many more have been strongly opposed to you in their sermons about the Sacrament.May you send me a short, firm letter and sharp reply.I will arrange for them to be sent to Martin and Philipp, with the accompanying request to reply.Adolf [Bitter], my nephew, has studied at Wittenberg and Brunswick recently, he was seen by us and has now gone again.He is greatly esteemed and says that Martin, Philipp, Pomeranus, Otto Brunsfeldius and many more have been strongly opposed to you in their sermons about the Sacrament.May you send me a short, firm letter and sharp reply.I will arrange for them to be sent to Martin and Philipp, with the accompanying request to reply.With this short letter I entrust you to Almighty God.

Dated at Cologne, 12th August, 32nd year.

Dirich [!] Bitter of Wipperfoird, schoolmaster of Saint Ursula.

To the esteemed and well-learned Master Heinrich Bullinger, my gracious friend, to hand.To the esteemed and well-learned Master Heinrich Bullinger, my gracious friend, to hand.At Zurich.</output>
 </seg>

