
 <seg id="1">
  <input>Der herr aller stercky stercke uns zuͦ diser zitt der nott und mere den globen in unns.Der herr aller stercky stercke uns zuͦ diser zitt der nott und mere den globen in unns.Amen.

O Bulliger, mir dis zitt ansechens onbekantt, so eß gott zuͦlast, als sinem ellenden werchzüg, sol ich üch sechen.O Bulliger, mir dis zitt ansechens onbekantt, so eß gott zuͦlast, als sinem ellenden werchzüg, sol ich üch sechen.Zuͦ diser zitt wil ich üch, wie ich vor gott schuldig bin und das on falsch, so war ich der säligkait beger, also nementz an, vor falschen bruͦdern und gaisternn, die alle crütz flüchend und nach zitlichem ruͦm, glüsten und gytz stellend und, so inen der stab in die hend wirtt oder inen nit gat nach irn glüsten, das crütz komptt, us irn toben köpffen - wie ogenschinlich ist - wütend gift uswerfend, lügend über die, so sy gliept habend, und vorhin vollen glisender, falscher lieby sind, die aber, gott syg lob, usbricht an allen ortten; und warlich kain bruͦderlich lieb in inen steckt, sonder sich inkoffend, bys sy gefrissend.O Bulliger, mir dis zitt ansechens onbekantt, so eß gott zuͦlast, als sinem ellenden werchzüg, sol ich üch sechen.Zuͦ diser zitt wil ich üch, wie ich vor gott schuldig bin und das on falsch, so war ich der säligkait beger, also nementz an, vor falschen bruͦdern und gaisternn, die alle crütz flüchend und nach zitlichem ruͦm, glüsten und gytz stellend und, so inen der stab in die hend wirtt oder inen nit gat nach irn glüsten, das crütz komptt, us irn toben köpffen - wie ogenschinlich ist - wütend gift uswerfend, lügend über die, so sy gliept habend, und vorhin vollen glisender, falscher lieby sind, die aber, gott syg lob, usbricht an allen ortten; und warlich kain bruͦderlich lieb in inen steckt, sonder sich inkoffend, bys sy gefrissend.O Karolstat oder Bodenstain, gott wirtt in treffen und offnen etc.

Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt, der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen.Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt, der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen.Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten, dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc.Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt, der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen.Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten, dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc.Der herr waist eß, ich red on hass.Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt, der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen.Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten, dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc.Der herr waist eß, ich red on hass.Warlich, warlich, gomend üch.Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt, der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen.Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten, dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc.Der herr waist eß, ich red on hass.Warlich, warlich, gomend üch.O Martine Luther, du hast in fil weg on zwifel fil müg ghept!

Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang.Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang.Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung.Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang.Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung.Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend.Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang.Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung.Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend.Gott erhalte uns!Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang.Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung.Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend.Gott erhalte uns!Waß nüws oder wie es stand etc. beger ich truwenß.</input>
  <output>O Lord of all strength, strengthen us in this time of need and save the world from us. O Lord of all strength, strengthen us in this time of need and save the world from us.Amen. I understand, dear brothers, how Lienhard Wirtt, who was faithful and a good leader, has reported to you certain articles in trust, and I have been sent to you to warn you. You must certainly observe this, for my request, as well as his and others, is to warn all brothers, especially a pious city like Zurich, etc. I understand, dear brothers, how Lienhard Wirtt, who was faithful and a good leader, has reported to you certain articles in trust, and I have been sent to you to warn you. You must certainly observe this, for my request, as well as his and others, is to warn all brothers, especially a pious city like Zurich, etc.The Lord knows that I speak out of hatred. I understand, dear brothers, how Lienhard Wirtt, who was faithful and a good leader, has reported to you certain articles in trust, and I have been sent to you to warn you. You must certainly observe this, for my request, as well as his and others, is to warn all brothers, especially a pious city like Zurich, etc.The Lord knows that I speak out of hatred. Truly, truly, I bid you farewell. O Martin Luther, you have certainly opened many ways without a doubt!

O Glorious Warrior, I am now seen as a petitioner, but I hope not for long. The state is - God be praised - well, yet with paternal examination. Greet the unknown schoolmaster from Bremgarten and others that you trust. God preserve us! What news or how it stands etc. I ask in trust.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang.Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung.Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend.Gott erhalte uns!Waß nüws oder wie es stand etc. beger ich truwenß.Min herr und bruͦder, Doctor Fadian, hat mir zuͦ gschriben, daß fergangen Strasburg, Ulm, Costentz, Basel - als im gsagt - zu Bern gsin etc.

Bittend gott für mich und unß alle.Bittend gott für mich und unß alle.Ich wolt von des gaistz wegen minem hernn und bruͦder, dem statschriber, gschriben han und gewarnt; so wais ich nit weders wäger, aber was üch und Lienharten och maister Hans Briner, dem ich och by geschriben, das thuͦnd, als obs hierin begriffen, och andre.

Behuͤt üch gott, lieber Bulliger, und ferlich üch, sin wort recht zu fuͤrnn, zuͦ buwen.Behuͤt üch gott, lieber Bulliger, und ferlich üch, sin wort recht zu fuͤrnn, zuͦ buwen.Amen.

In welchem hus ir sind, wondert mich.

Actum im land Appenzell, uff mittwoch nach Sebastiani anno 31 jar.

Uwer armer diener Hans Vogler.

Um kürtze willen hab ich maister Hans Briner uf dis gschrift gewisen, by üch zuͦ hörn, ze warnen etc.

An min geliepttenn im hernn, Hainrichen Bullinger, prediger der gemain der statt Zürych, minem günstigen herrenn etc.</input>
  <output>Greetings, Bullinger, I am presently considered a preacher, but hope not for long. Thank God, I am doing well, albeit with paternal care. Greet the unknown schoolmaster of Bremgarten and others who trust you. May God preserve us! I ask trustingly for what news or how the situation is, etc. My lord and brother, Doctor Fadian, has written to me that he went to Strasbourg, Ulm, Constance, Basel, as he said, to Bern etc.

I pray God for myself and all of us. I would have written to my lord and brother, the state scribe, and warned him out of spirit; but I know not wither, but what you and Lienharten, also Master Hans Briner, whom I have also written to, do, as if it were included in this, also the others.

May God protect you, dear Bullinger, and take care that you faithfully fulfill His word. Amen.

I wonder in which house you are.

Done in the land of Appenzell, on Wednesday after Sebastian, in year 31.

Your poor servant Hans Vogler.

For brevity's sake I have made Master Hans Briner aware of this writing to hear and warn you etc.

To my beloved in the Lord, Heinrich Bullinger, preacher of the congregation of the city of Zurich, my gracious Lord etc.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="1">
  <input>Der herr aller stercky stercke uns zuͦ diser zitt der nott und mere den globen in unns . Der herr aller stercky stercke uns zuͦ diser zitt der nott und mere den globen in unns . Amen.

 O Bulliger, mir dis zitt ansechens onbekantt, so eß gott zuͦlast, als sinem ellenden werchzüg, sol ich üch sechen . O Bulliger, mir dis zitt ansechens onbekantt, so eß gott zuͦlast, als sinem ellenden werchzüg, sol ich üch sechen . Zuͦ diser zitt wil ich üch, wie ich vor gott schuldig bin und das on falsch, so war ich der säligkait beger, also nementz an, vor falschen bruͦdern und gaisternn , die alle crütz flüchend und nach zitlichem ruͦm, glüsten und gytz stellend und, so inen der stab in die hend wirtt oder inen nit gat nach irn glüsten, das crütz komptt, us irn toben köpffen - wie ogenschinlich ist - wütend gift uswerfend , lügend über die, so sy gliept habend, und vorhin vollen glisender , falscher lieby sind, die aber, gott syg lob, usbricht an allen ortten; und warlich kain bruͦderlich lieb in inen steckt, sonder sich inkoffend , bys sy gefrissend . O Bulliger, mir dis zitt ansechens onbekantt, so eß gott zuͦlast, als sinem ellenden werchzüg, sol ich üch sechen . Zuͦ diser zitt wil ich üch, wie ich vor gott schuldig bin und das on falsch, so war ich der säligkait beger, also nementz an, vor falschen bruͦdern und gaisternn , die alle crütz flüchend und nach zitlichem ruͦm, glüsten und gytz stellend und, so inen der stab in die hend wirtt oder inen nit gat nach irn glüsten, das crütz komptt, us irn toben köpffen - wie ogenschinlich ist - wütend gift uswerfend , lügend über die, so sy gliept habend, und vorhin vollen glisender , falscher lieby sind, die aber, gott syg lob, usbricht an allen ortten; und warlich kain bruͦderlich lieb in inen steckt, sonder sich inkoffend , bys sy gefrissend . O Karolstat oder Bodenstain , gott wirtt in treffen und offnen etc.

 Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt , der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen. Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt , der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen. Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten , dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc. Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt , der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen. Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten , dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc. Der herr waist eß, ich red on hass. Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt , der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen. Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten , dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc. Der herr waist eß, ich red on hass. Warlich, warlich, gomend üch . Daß ferstond ir, lieber bruͦder, wie üch Lienhardy Wirtt , der getrüw, war, guͦter zügny üch fertruwenß wis ettlich artickel berichten, und ich in harum zuͦ üch abgefertigt hab zuͦ warnen. Von dem wellend ir ja ja halten , dann min beger, och sin und andrer, alle bruͦder zuͦ warnen, sonderß och ain frome statt Zürych etc. Der herr waist eß, ich red on hass. Warlich, warlich, gomend üch . O Martine Luther , du hast in fil weg on zwifel fil müg ghept !

 Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang. Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang. Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung . Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang. Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung . Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend. Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang. Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung . Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend. Gott erhalte uns! Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang. Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung . Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend. Gott erhalte uns! Waß nüws oder wie es stand etc. beger ich truwenß .</input>
  <output>Lord of all strength, strengthen us in this time of need and save us from the world. Lord of all strength, strengthen us in this time of need and save us from the world. Amen. 

Oh Valiant One, this time is unknown to me, so by God's will, as His destitute work, I seek you. Oh Valiant One, this time is unknown to me, so by God's will, as His destitute work, I seek you. At this time I want to ask you, as I am obligated to God and without deception, to be a beggar of salvation, so accept me, from false brothers and strangers, all cursing the cross and, after a short time, longing and desiring gold, and if the staff is put in their hands, or does not get them to their desire, the cross comes out of their raging heads - how clearly visible it is - throwing out angry poison, lying about those they have embraced, and before full of sweet, false loves, which however, praised be to God, breaks out in all places; and truly no brotherly love is in them, but rather they take, until they are satisfied. Oh Valiant One, this time is unknown to me, so by God's will, as His destitute work, I seek you. At this time I want to ask you, as I am obligated to God and without deception, to be a beggar of salvation, so accept me, from false brothers and strangers, all cursing the cross and, after a short time, longing and desiring gold, and if the staff is put in their hands, or does not get them to their desire, the cross comes out of their raging heads - how clearly visible it is - throwing out angry poison, lying about those they have embraced, and before full of sweet, false loves, which however, praised be to God, breaks out in all places; and truly no brotherly love is in them, but rather they take, until they are satisfied. O Charlesstadt or Bodenstain, God will meet and open, etc.

Understand this, dear brother, how Lienhard Wirtt, the faithful, good-natured, with good trust may tell you a few articles, and I have sent them to you to warn. Understand this, dear brother, how Lienhard Wirtt, the faithful, good-natured, with good trust may tell you a few articles, and I have sent them to you to warn. You should certainly keep to that, then my beggar, as well as his and others, all brothers to warn, besides also a pious city of Zurich, etc. Understand this, dear brother, how Lienhard Wirtt, the faithful, good-natured, with good trust may tell you a few articles, and I have sent them to you to warn. You should certainly keep to that, then my beggar, as well as his and others, all brothers to warn, besides also a pious city of Zurich, etc. The Lord knows it, I speak out of hatred. Understand this, dear brother, how Lienhard Wirtt, the faithful, good-natured, with good trust may tell you a few articles, and I have sent them to you to warn. You should certainly keep to that, then my beggar, as well as his and others, all brothers to warn, besides also a pious city of Zurich, etc. The Lord knows it, I speak out of hatred. Truly, truly, I greet you. Understand this, dear brother, how Lienhard Wirtt, the faithful, good-natured, with good trust may tell you a few articles, and I have sent them to you to warn. You should certainly keep to that, then my beggar, as well as his and others, all brothers to warn, besides also a pious city of Zurich, etc. The Lord knows it, I speak out of hatred. Truly, truly, I greet you. O Martin Luther, you have certainly saved many in a difficult way!

Beloved Valiant One, I am currently considered a beggar, but I hope not for long. Beloved Valiant One, I am currently considered a beggar, but I hope not for long. State is - praise be to God - well, yet with fatherly temptation. Beloved Valiant One, I am currently considered a beggar, but I hope not for long. State is - praise be to God - well, yet with fatherly temptation. Greet the unknown schoolmaster of Bremgarten and others, whom you trust. Beloved Valiant One, I am currently considered a beggar, but I hope not for long. State is - praise be to God - well, yet with fatherly temptation. Greet the unknown schoolmaster of Bremgarten and others, whom you trust. God preserve us! Beloved Valiant One, I am currently considered a beggar, but I hope not for long. State is - praise be to God - well, yet with fatherly temptation. Greet the unknown schoolmaster of Bremgarten and others, whom you trust. God preserve us! What news or how it stands, etc. I request trustingly.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Gliepter Bulliger, ich bin jetzemal ain pandit angesechen, aber hoff, nit lang. Stat och - gott sy lob - wol, doch mitt fätterlicher fersuͦchung . Gruͤssend mir den onbekanten schulthais von Bremgarten und ander, so ir fertruwend. Gott erhalte uns! Waß nüws oder wie es stand etc. beger ich truwenß . Min herr und bruͦder, Doctor Fadian , hat mir zuͦ gschriben , daß fergangen Strasburg , Ulm , Costentz , Basel - als im gsagt - zu Bern gsin etc.

 Bittend gott für mich und unß alle. Bittend gott für mich und unß alle. Ich wolt von des gaistz wegen minem hernn und bruͦder, dem statschriber , gschriben han und gewarnt; so wais ich nit weders wäger , aber was üch und Lienharten och maister Hans Briner , dem ich och by geschriben , das thuͦnd, als obs hierin begriffen , och andre.

 Behuͤt üch gott, lieber Bulliger, und ferlich üch, sin wort recht zu fuͤrnn, zuͦ buwen. Behuͤt üch gott, lieber Bulliger, und ferlich üch, sin wort recht zu fuͤrnn, zuͦ buwen. Amen.

 In welchem hus ir sind, wondert mich.

 Actum im land Appenzell, uff mittwoch nach Sebastiani anno 31 jar.

 Uwer armer diener Hans Vogler .

 Um kürtze willen hab ich maister Hans Briner uf dis gschrift gewisen, by üch zuͦ hörn, ze warnen etc.

 An min geliepttenn im hernn, Hainrichen Bullinger, prediger der gemain der statt Zürych, minem günstigen herrenn etc.</input>
  <output>Greetings to you, beloved Bulliger, I am currently considered a pandit, but hope not to be for long. I am doing well, thanks be to God, albeit with some fatigue. Greet my unknown schoolteacher from Bremgarten and others, whom you trust. God preserve us! I request news or whatever the situation is etc. My lord and brother, Doctor Fadian, has written to me that he has been to Strasburg, Ulm, Costentz, Basel - as it was said - to Bern etc.

I pray to God for me and all of us. I wanted to write to my lord and brother, the statesman, from the spirit and warn him; I did not know any messenger, however whatever you and Lienharten and master Hans Briner, whom I have also written to, do, if it is included here, and others.

God protect you, dear Bulliger, and be careful to keep God's word correctly. Amen.

I wonder in which house you are.

Done in the land of Appenzell, on Wednesday after Sebastiani in the 31st year.

Your poor servant Hans Vogler.

For brevity's sake I have pointed out to Master Hans Briner on this writing to listen to you, to warn etc.</output>
 </seg>

