
 <seg id="1">
  <input>S.S.Lieber bruͤder Heinrich.

Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han.Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han.Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen, biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat.Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han.Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen, biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat.Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil, des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand.Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han.Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen, biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat.Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil, des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand.Welte gott, daß herr Röst ein bott wäry; by den unsern weiß ich uff dise zit kein angnemeren.Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han.Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen, biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat.Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil, des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand.Welte gott, daß herr Röst ein bott wäry; by den unsern weiß ich uff dise zit kein angnemeren.Doch ob schon da nütt usgericht, wirt doch das ein ungezwiflet mittel sin zuͦ einer bestendigen concordi, namlich daß die von Schaffhusen und Basel zuͤ unß kartind, umm semliche concordi ersuͤchtind, und so inen die verlangete, als dann sy allen blast beeder stetten hinwäg und abstaltind.Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen.Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han.Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen, biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat.Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil, des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand.Welte gott, daß herr Röst ein bott wäry; by den unsern weiß ich uff dise zit kein angnemeren.Doch ob schon da nütt usgericht, wirt doch das ein ungezwiflet mittel sin zuͦ einer bestendigen concordi, namlich daß die von Schaffhusen und Basel zuͤ unß kartind, umm semliche concordi ersuͤchtind, und so inen die verlangete, als dann sy allen blast beeder stetten hinwäg und abstaltind.Si hend ouch umm unsertwillen übel gelitten; so sind sy lindmuͤtiger und beeden stetten angenäm und geachtet.

Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg; acht, der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist, ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen.Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg; acht, der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist, ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen.Erario nitt so vil; aber Wagner, Trempen, buwherr Ougspurger, Vischer, Petro Cirono dem stattschriber alle ding wol ze vertrüwen.Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg; acht, der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist, ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen.Erario nitt so vil; aber Wagner, Trempen, buwherr Ougspurger, Vischer, Petro Cirono dem stattschriber alle ding wol ze vertrüwen.Schrib ich darum, so du etwa wil ze schrieben habist, wissist wäm.Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg; acht, der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist, ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen.Erario nitt so vil; aber Wagner, Trempen, buwherr Ougspurger, Vischer, Petro Cirono dem stattschriber alle ding wol ze vertrüwen.Schrib ich darum, so du etwa wil ze schrieben habist, wissist wäm.Interim Erarius non est negligendus, nam sentio hominem suę prudentię sic innixum, ut quicquid non geratur vel suo consilio vel ipso conscio, omnibus renitatur viribus.

Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben.Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben.Ir antwurt: si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen.</input>
  <output>Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben.Ir antwurt: si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen.Das hend wir gäben und finden, daß es wol gschriben, daß es im ganzen weit bekandt.

Dear Brother Heinrich,

I have understood your diligent and earnest letter and given it to be read to those whom I think trustworthy. And I find that with time we will also be reconciled. It is necessary to stroke the bear until it becomes calm and gentle and lays down its fierceness. On the same day, young Jacob of Wattenwil, whose Christian heart is well known to you, is sent with suitable orders, as I understand. May God be willing that Herr Röst be a messenger; among ours I know of none more suitable at this time. Even if nothing is accomplished, this will nevertheless be an undoubted means of establishing a lasting concord, namely that those from Schaffhausen and Basel come to us to ask for the same concord and that they then take away all the differences of both places and make them cease. They have also suffered ill on our account; therefore they are more gentle and acceptable and respected by both places.

Therefore, I write to you out of concern; take heed that Imm Hag informs you further, for he is very active in this affair and more earnest and trustworthy than others. Erario is not so much; but Wagner, Trempen, Burgher Ougspurger, Vischer, and Secretary Petro Cirono are all trustworthy. Therefore, if you have something to write, you know to whom. Meanwhile, Erario is not to be neglected, for I sense that he is so attached to his own prudence that he resists everything that is not done with his advice or with his knowledge.

Therefore, on account of the book, our lords have written to Lucern. Their answer: they know nothing of it; we should inquire of the printer. We have done so and find that it is well written and widely known.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben.Ir antwurt: si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen.Ist ouch allen 5 orten und jetlichen insunders geschriben von deren von Bremgarten wägen.Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben.Ir antwurt: si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen.Ist ouch allen 5 orten und jetlichen insunders geschriben von deren von Bremgarten wägen.Ein schlächte antwurt wider gäben, als ob sy dessi macht und gwalt habind; doch wellind si nach der heilgen zitt entlich antwurt gäben.Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben.Ir antwurt: si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen.Ist ouch allen 5 orten und jetlichen insunders geschriben von deren von Bremgarten wägen.Ein schlächte antwurt wider gäben, als ob sy dessi macht und gwalt habind; doch wellind si nach der heilgen zitt entlich antwurt gäben.Acht wol, man werde in disen comitiis rätig werden.

Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt.Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt.Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt.Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt.Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt.Wellist herinn handlen, daß der trucker nitt kent werde, dann dir ist wol ingedenck, was Adamo Petro begegnet a Lucernatibus.Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt.Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt.Wellist herinn handlen, daß der trucker nitt kent werde, dann dir ist wol ingedenck, was Adamo Petro begegnet a Lucernatibus.Wir mögend wol antwurt liden, ist ouch von nöten.Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt.Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt.Wellist herinn handlen, daß der trucker nitt kent werde, dann dir ist wol ingedenck, was Adamo Petro begegnet a Lucernatibus.Wir mögend wol antwurt liden, ist ouch von nöten.Aber nitt vil eeren wirst von unß schriben, also evangelisch und dess eergits ledig sind wir worden.

Ich bitt dich, wellist dem Sepiano, id est Imm Hag, bald antwurten, dann er sich dines schribenß wol frewt und vermag.Ich bitt dich, wellist dem Sepiano, id est Imm Hag, bald antwurten, dann er sich dines schribenß wol frewt und vermag.Diner herren früntlich schriben hatt vil bewegt; ursachen unsers unwillens wirst by bilegtem brieff verston.

Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia.</input>
  <output>Accordingly, our lords have written to Lucerne about the book. Their answer: they know nothing about it; we should ask the printer. It is also written in all five places and particularly by the ones from Bremgarten. Accordingly, our lords have written to Lucerne about the book. Their answer: they know nothing about it; we should ask the printer. It is also written in all five places and particularly by the ones from Bremgarten.They gave a bad answer, as if they held this power and authority; however, they would finally give an answer after the holy time. Accordingly, our lords have written to Lucerne about the book. Their answer: they know nothing about it; we should ask the printer. It is also written in all five places and particularly by the ones from Bremgarten.They gave a bad answer, as if they held this power and authority; however, they would finally give an answer after the holy time.Take note, something will be decided in these comitia.

The answer regarding the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some of us think it should be called "Kressich" because it will be called lettuce. The answer regarding the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some of us think it should be called "Kressich" because it will be called lettuce.There are bears of a variety with us. The answer regarding the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some of us think it should be called "Kressich" because it will be called lettuce.There are bears of a variety with us.Take care that the printer is not known, then you remember well what happened to Adamo Petro in Lucerne. The answer regarding the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some of us think it should be called "Kressich" because it will be called lettuce.There are bears of a variety with us.Take care that the printer is not known, then you remember well what happened to Adamo Petro in Lucerne.We can endure an answer, it is also necessary. The answer regarding the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some of us think it should be called "Kressich" because it will be called lettuce.There are bears of a variety with us.Take care that the printer is not known, then you remember well what happened to Adamo Petro in Lucerne.We can endure an answer, it is also necessary.But we will not write much honor to you, so that we are become free from the gospel and its honor.

I beg you to answer Sepiano, that is Imm Hag, soon, then he will be pleased with your letter and be able to do it. I beg you to answer Sepiano, that is Imm Hag, soon, then he will be pleased with your letter and be able to do it.Your lords' letter has moved much; the causes of our unwillingness are understood by the enclosed letter.

We cannot prevent the Gotshußlüten, because one must expect their arrival. We cannot prevent the Gotshußlüten, because one must expect their arrival.They stand ready to govern the four places. We cannot prevent the Gotshußlüten, because one must expect their arrival.They stand ready to govern the four places.Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be brought back. We cannot prevent the Gotshußlüten, because one must expect their arrival.They stand ready to govern the four places.Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be brought back.I fear that the Immotani will not allow any, as we too in the former peace in the article concerning the word of God. We cannot prevent the Gotshußlüten, because one must expect their arrival.They stand ready to govern the four places.Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be brought back.I fear that the Immotani will not allow any, as we too in the former peace in the article concerning the word of God.This is from Erario and Sępiano. We cannot prevent the Gotshußlüten, because one must expect their arrival.They stand ready to govern the four places.Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be brought back.I fear that the Immotani will not allow any, as we too in the former peace in the article concerning the word of God.This is from Erario and Sępiano.In short: the old legates, senators, cerdones, and papists are sent to the comitia.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="3">
  <input>Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia.Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets, quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia.Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets, quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia.Ach, daß gott erbarm dess kriegs: wie hett er so vil hertzen ummkert.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia.Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets, quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia.Ach, daß gott erbarm dess kriegs: wie hett er so vil hertzen ummkert.Jetz weiß ich aber nitt wyter.Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen, dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten.Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen.Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden.Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia.Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets, quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia.Ach, daß gott erbarm dess kriegs: wie hett er so vil hertzen ummkert.Jetz weiß ich aber nitt wyter.Dominus vias tuas dirigat, in sui nominis gloriam, evangelii profectum et patrię salutem.

Vale.

Ultima martii.

Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen.Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen.Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys.Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen.Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys.Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio.Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen.Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys.Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio.Reliqua ex Rellicano.Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen.Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys.Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio.Reliqua ex Rellicano.Salutat te Kolbius et alii.Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam.Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen.Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys.Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio.Reliqua ex Rellicano.Salutat te Kolbius et alii.Rursum vale.

Anno 32.

Saluta Pellicanum, Leonem, Carolstadium et alios.

Tuum minimum numisma.

Heinrico Bullingero, ecclesiastę Tigurino, fratri suo charissimo.</input>
  <output>We cannot avoid the services of the court, then we must expect the imposition.It stands for the four places to be administered.But if an explanation of the peace is desired, it is not possible; it must be brought back.I fear the Immotani will not allow it, as we also did in the previous peace regarding the article of God's word.Hec ex Erario et Sępiano.In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia.Therefore, we are always breaking beside, because it is also done in the elections; for they are so concealed that we receive nothing, unless other elections are already sought.Ah, that God may have mercy on the war: how many hearts have been turned.Now I know no further.May the Lord direct your paths, to the glory of his name, the advancement of the gospel, and the safety of the country.Farewell.Last of March.Your ex senate have written a long letter to Megander concerning the mass.I fear the French mass will then the papal.It breaks me always the laugh and the scream.Today the feet have again fulfilled their office.The rest from Rellicano.Salutat you Kolbius and others.Farewell again.Year 32.Salutate Pellicanum, Leonem, Carolstadium et alios.Your minimum coin.To Heinrico Bullingero, the Tigurine clergyman, his dearest brother.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="1">
  <input>S. S. Lieber bruͤder Heinrich.

 Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han. Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han. Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen , biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat. Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han. Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen , biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat. Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil , des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand. Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han. Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen , biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat. Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil , des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand. Welte gott, daß herr Röst ein bott wäry; by den unsern weiß ich uff dise zit kein angnemeren. Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han. Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen , biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat. Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil , des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand. Welte gott, daß herr Röst ein bott wäry; by den unsern weiß ich uff dise zit kein angnemeren. Doch ob schon da nütt usgericht, wirt doch das ein ungezwiflet mittel sin zuͦ einer bestendigen concordi, namlich daß die von Schaffhusen und Basel zuͤ unß kartind , umm semliche concordi ersuͤchtind, und so inen die verlangete , als dann sy allen blast beeder stetten hinwäg und abstaltind . Din flissig ernstlich schriben hab ich verstanden und ze läsen gäben denen, so mich bedunckt ze vertrüwen. Und finden, daß mitt der zit wir och werdint verkudret han. Man muͤß dem bären krätzlen , biß das er zam und guͤtig wirt, sin grimmen ablat. Man schickt uff den tag gen Arouw juncker Jacoben von Wattenwil , des christelich hertz dir wol bekant, mitt zimlichen befelch, als ich verstand. Welte gott, daß herr Röst ein bott wäry; by den unsern weiß ich uff dise zit kein angnemeren. Doch ob schon da nütt usgericht, wirt doch das ein ungezwiflet mittel sin zuͦ einer bestendigen concordi, namlich daß die von Schaffhusen und Basel zuͤ unß kartind , umm semliche concordi ersuͤchtind, und so inen die verlangete , als dann sy allen blast beeder stetten hinwäg und abstaltind . Si hend ouch umm unsertwillen übel gelitten ; so sind sy lindmuͤtiger und beeden stetten angenäm und geachtet.

 Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg ; acht , der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist , ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen. Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg ; acht , der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist , ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen. Erario nitt so vil; aber Wagner , Trempen , buwherr Ougspurger , Vischer , Petro Cirono dem stattschriber alle ding wol ze vertrüwen. Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg ; acht , der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist , ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen. Erario nitt so vil; aber Wagner , Trempen , buwherr Ougspurger , Vischer , Petro Cirono dem stattschriber alle ding wol ze vertrüwen. Schrib ich darum, so du etwa wil ze schrieben habist, wissist wäm. Das schrib dir uff ein fürsorg ; acht , der Imm Hag berichte dich wyter, dann er je für ander all ifrig in dem handel und ernstiger ist , ouch imm für ander ze vertrüwen. Erario nitt so vil; aber Wagner , Trempen , buwherr Ougspurger , Vischer , Petro Cirono dem stattschriber alle ding wol ze vertrüwen. Schrib ich darum, so du etwa wil ze schrieben habist, wissist wäm. Interim Erarius non est negligendus, nam sentio hominem suę prudentię sic innixum, ut quicquid non geratur vel suo consilio vel ipso conscio, omnibus renitatur viribus.

 Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben . Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben . Ir antwurt : si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen.</input>
  <output>Dear Brother Heinrich, 

I have understood your diligent and earnest writing and given it to those whom I deem trustworthy to read. And I find that in the meantime we will also be reconciled. One must stroke the bear until he becomes gentle and his rage subsides. On the same day, young Jacob from Wattenwil, whose Christian heart you know well, was sent with considerable orders, as I understand. May God that Mr. Röst be a messenger; I know of none more suitable among ours at this time. Although nothing has been done yet, it will certainly be an undoubted means to a lasting agreement, namely that the people of Schaffhausen and Basel will come to us to ask for such an agreement and then they will put away all quarrels of both cities. They have also suffered evil on our behalf; so they are more gentle and agreeable and respected by both cities. 

This is the letter to you; take care that Imm Hag reports to you further, as he is very busy in dealing and is more serious and trustworthy than others. Erario does not do so much; but Wagner, Trempen, builder Ougspurger, Vischer, and Petro Cirono, the scribe, are all trustworthy. If you have anything to write, you know who. Meanwhile, Erarius must not be neglected, for I feel that he is so attached to his own prudence that whatever is not done with his advice or with his knowledge, he will resist with all his strength.

Therefore, on behalf of the book, our lords have written to Lucern. Their answer was that they knew nothing about it and we should ask the printer.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="2">
  <input>Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben . Ir antwurt : si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen. Ist ouch allen 5 orten und jetlichen insunders geschriben von deren von Bremgarten wägen . Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben . Ir antwurt : si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen. Ist ouch allen 5 orten und jetlichen insunders geschriben von deren von Bremgarten wägen . Ein schlächte antwurt wider gäben, als ob sy dessi macht und gwalt habind ; doch wellind si nach der heilgen zitt entlich antwurt gäben. Demnach dess buͤchlins halb habend unser herren gen Lucern gschriben . Ir antwurt : si wissend nütt darvon; wir söllind dem trucker nachfragen. Ist ouch allen 5 orten und jetlichen insunders geschriben von deren von Bremgarten wägen . Ein schlächte antwurt wider gäben, als ob sy dessi macht und gwalt habind ; doch wellind si nach der heilgen zitt entlich antwurt gäben. Acht wol, man werde in disen comitiis rätig werden.

 Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt . Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt . Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt. Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt . Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt. Wellist herinn handlen, daß der trucker nitt kent werde, dann dir ist wol ingedenck, was Adamo Petro begegnet a Lucernatibus . Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt . Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt. Wellist herinn handlen, daß der trucker nitt kent werde, dann dir ist wol ingedenck, was Adamo Petro begegnet a Lucernatibus . Wir mögend wol antwurt liden , ist ouch von nöten. Der antwurt halb uff den «Tanngrozen» frag nitt vil, wiewol ettlich by unß meinind, es sölle «Kressich» genempt werden, die wil der sich Salat nempt . Es sind by unß bären von gschlächt. Wellist herinn handlen, daß der trucker nitt kent werde, dann dir ist wol ingedenck, was Adamo Petro begegnet a Lucernatibus . Wir mögend wol antwurt liden , ist ouch von nöten. Aber nitt vil eeren wirst von unß schriben, also evangelisch und dess eergits ledig sind wir worden.

 Ich bitt dich, wellist dem Sepiano , id est Imm Hag, bald antwurten, dann er sich dines schribenß wol frewt und vermag . Ich bitt dich, wellist dem Sepiano , id est Imm Hag, bald antwurten, dann er sich dines schribenß wol frewt und vermag . Diner herren früntlich schriben hatt vil bewegt ; ursachen unsers unwillens wirst by bilegtem brieff verston.

 Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia .</input>
  <output>Accordingly, our lords had written to Lucerne about the half of the book. Their answer was that they knew nothing about it; we should ask the trucker. It was also written to all 5 places and each one in particular from those of Bremgarten. Accordingly, our lords had written to Lucerne about the half of the book. Their answer was that they knew nothing about it; we should ask the trucker. It was also written to all 5 places and each one in particular from those of Bremgarten. They gave a bad answer, as if they had this power and authority; yet they wanted to finally give an answer after the holy time. Accordingly, our lords had written to Lucerne about the half of the book. Their answer was that they knew nothing about it; we should ask the trucker. It was also written to all 5 places and each one in particular from those of Bremgarten. They gave a bad answer, as if they had this power and authority; yet they wanted to finally give an answer after the holy time. Take care that something will be decided in these comitiis.

The answer about the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some among us thought that it should be called "Kressich", because that is the name of the salad. There are bears of different kinds among us. The answer about the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some among us thought that it should be called "Kressich", because that is the name of the salad. There are bears of different kinds among us. Deal with it so that the trucker will not be known, then you will remember what happened to Adamo Petro at the Lucernatibus. The answer about the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some among us thought that it should be called "Kressich", because that is the name of the salad. There are bears of different kinds among us. Deal with it so that the trucker will not be known, then you will remember what happened to Adamo Petro at the Lucernatibus. We can well endure the answer, it is also necessary. The answer about the "Tanngrozen" does not ask much, although some among us thought that it should be called "Kressich", because that is the name of the salad. There are bears of different kinds among us. Deal with it so that the trucker will not be known, then you will remember what happened to Adamo Petro at the Lucernatibus. We can well endure the answer, it is also necessary. But not much honor will be written from us, so we have become free of the evangelical and the honorable.

I ask you to answer Sepiano, that is Imm Hag, soon, for he will be pleased with your writing and is able to. I ask you to answer Sepiano, that is Imm Hag, soon, for he will be pleased with your writing and is able to. Your lords' letter has moved much; the reason for our unwillingness will be understood by the enclosed letter.

We can do nothing about the god's servants, then one must wait for the outcome. We can do nothing about the god's servants, then one must wait for the outcome. They stand to manage the 4 places. We can do nothing about the god's servants, then one must wait for the outcome. They stand to manage the 4 places. Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be put off. We can do nothing about the god's servants, then one must wait for the outcome. They stand to manage the 4 places. Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be put off. I fear that the Immotani will not permit it, as we have also been released from the article of God's word in the previous peace. We can do nothing about the god's servants, then one must wait for the outcome. They stand to manage the 4 places. Where, however, an explanation of the peace is requested, it is not possible; it must be put off. I fear that the Immotani will not permit it, as we have also been released from the article of God's word in the previous peace. This from the Erario and Sepiano.

In short: old legates, senetiones, cerdones, papists are sent to the comitia.</output>
 </seg>


 <seg id="3">
  <input>Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia . Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets , quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia. Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia . Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets , quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia. Ach, daß gott erbarm dess kriegs: wie hett er so vil hertzen ummkert . Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia . Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets , quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia. Ach, daß gott erbarm dess kriegs: wie hett er so vil hertzen ummkert . Jetz weiß ich aber nitt wyter. Der gotshußlüten halb mögend wir nütt fürkummen , dann man muͤß dess anbringens erwarten. Si stond den 4 orten ze verwaltigen . Wo aber ein erlütrung dess frideß begärt, ist nitt möglich; muͤß hinder sich gebracht werden . Ich sorg, die Immotani werdint keine zuͤlassen, als ouch wir in vordrigem friden in dem artikel gottes wort beträffend . Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia . Darum bricht unß allwäg näbenbrets , quod etiam in comitiis agitur; nam ita celantur, ut nihil accipiamus, nisi cum alia iam petenda sunt comitia. Ach, daß gott erbarm dess kriegs: wie hett er so vil hertzen ummkert . Jetz weiß ich aber nitt wyter. Dominus vias tuas dirigat , in sui nominis gloriam, evangelii profectum et patrię salutem.

 Vale.

 Ultima martii.

 Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen. Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen. Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys . Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen. Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys . Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio. Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen. Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys . Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio. Reliqua ex Rellicano. Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen. Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys . Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio. Reliqua ex Rellicano. Salutat te Kolbius et alii. Tui ex senatu longam epistolam scripserunt ad Megandrum propter missam. Ich förcht die französischen mess wirß dann die bäpstlichen. Bricht mich allwäg der löffen und dess gschreys . Hodie pedes rursum suo functi sunt officio. Reliqua ex Rellicano. Salutat te Kolbius et alii. Rursum vale.

 Anno 32.

 Saluta Pellicanum , Leonem , Carolstadium et alios.

 Tuum minimum numisma.

 Heinrico Bullingero, ecclesiastę Tigurino, fratri suo charissimo.</input>
  <output>We cannot avoid the Gotshußlüten, we must expect their arrival. They are appointed to administer the four places. But if an explanation of the peace is desired, it is not possible; it must be kept to oneself. I fear the Immotani will not allow it, as we did in the previous peace concerning the article of God's word. Hec ex Erario et Sępiano. In summa: legati veteres, senetiones, cerdones, papistę mittuntur ad comitia. Therefore, we are constantly deprived, as it is also discussed at the comitia; for they are so hidden that we receive nothing unless other comitia are already to be requested. Oh that God would have mercy on the war: how many hearts he has overturned. Now I do not know any further. May the Lord direct your ways, for the glory of his name, the progress of the gospel and the salvation of the country. Farewell. Last of March.

Your senators have written a long letter to Megandrum concerning the mass. I fear the French mass more than the papal one. Constantly the laughter and the shouting breaks me. Today the feet have again fulfilled their duty. The remaining from Rellicano. Kolbius and others salute you. Again farewell. Year 32. Greet Pellicanum, Leonem, Carolstadium and others. Your smallest coin.

To Heinrico Bullinger, the Tigurine clergyman, dearest brother.</output>
 </seg>

